<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A ievvell for gentrie Being an exact dictionary, or true method, to make any man vnderstand all the art, secrets, and worthy knowledges belonging to hawking, hunting, fouling and fishing. Together with all the true measures for winding of the horne. Now newly published, and beautified with all the rarest experiments that are knowne or practised at this day.</title>
            <author>T. S., fl. 1614.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1614</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 84 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 50 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11257</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21520</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110758</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846239</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846239</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11193</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11257)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11193)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1218:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A ievvell for gentrie Being an exact dictionary, or true method, to make any man vnderstand all the art, secrets, and worthy knowledges belonging to hawking, hunting, fouling and fishing. Together with all the true measures for winding of the horne. Now newly published, and beautified with all the rarest experiments that are knowne or practised at this day.</title>
                  <author>T. S., fl. 1614.</author>
                  <author>Berners, Juliana, b. 1388? Boke of Saint Albans.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[100] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By Thomas Snodham] for Iohn Helme, and are to be sold at his shop in St. Dunstanes Church-yard in Fleetstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1614.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: T.S.</note>
                  <note>Based on the Boke of Saint Albans, which is attributed to Juliana Berners.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-M⁴ N² .</note>
                  <note>"A briefe treatise of fowling" and "A briefe treatise of fishing" each have separate dated title pages; register is continuous.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of a photostat of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Falconry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Hunting --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Fishing --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:11193:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11193:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>A Ievvell for Gentrie.</p>
                  <p>Being an exact Dictionary, or true Method, to make any Man vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand all the Art, Secrets, and worthy Knowledges belonging to Hawking, Hunting, Fowling and Fiſhing. Together with all the true Meaſures for Winding of the HORNE.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Now newly publiſhed, and beautified with all the rareſt exper<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ts that are knowne or practiſed at this Day.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>depiction of a few men hunting</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p>Printed at London <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ohn H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> and are to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>old at his ſhop in St. Dunſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>anes Church-yard in Fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>reet. 1614.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:11193:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11193:2"/>
                  <head>TO THE RIGHT Worſhipfull M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
                     <hi>John Tooke,</hi> one of the Auditors of his Maieſties Courts of Wards and Liueries.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>YR: Bookes that in times paſt were accounted the Nobleſt Tributes which could come to the hands of Vertue, are now either in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſo disfigured, or by ignorance ſo ſleightly eſteemed, that Goodneſſe is halfe afraid to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare before great men; yet I that know the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of your temper, euer readie to adorne any ſhadow of modeſt and good proportion, am bold, out of my beſt loue, to ſolicite you with this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment, in which is matter worthy your eare, being indeed thoſe abſolute parts of Muſicke which make perfect the harmony of a true Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman. I doe not offer it as a diſturber of your
<pb facs="tcp:11193:3"/> more ſerious Meditations, but as an attendant, to wait the leaſure of thoſe good houres, when you ſhall vnbend your minde from the troubles of grauer buſines, then to recreate and erect your ſpirits with the exerciſes of theſe wholeſome and well-allowed pleaſures. I need not runne into any gloſſe or commendations of their natures, ſince the vſe and allowance thereof (being ſeldome or neuer accompanied without vertue) are Letters-Patents of ſuch ſtrength as no malice, or ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of life can infrindge or make of leſſe value then an ample goodneſſe. What euer they are, yours they now are, and with them my ſelfe euer to be diſpoſed by you.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Worſhips euer at command. <hi>T. S.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:11193:3"/>
                  <head>To the Reader.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Collection (Gentle Reader) how euer in former Impreſſions diſmem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred and rob'd of his beſt lynaments by an vnskilfull Regiſter, or a more ignorant workeman (both being farre to ſeeke in the Arts, and in the Antiquitie of the the Phraſe) was notwithſtanding in it's firſt birth the childe of the moſt excellenteſt Father that euer begot, in memory, any worke of this nature, and was for the glory thereof the firſt booke that euer was Printed in this Kingdome, as may appeare by the record of Bookes then Printed at Saint <hi>Albons.</hi> Now for as much as the defects were ſo groſſe that <hi>Treſtram</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe would hardly haue knowne ſo neare a kinſman, I haue for the worlds generall ſatisfaction reduc't it ſo truely to the naturall beautie of his owne Parents, that not the ſeuereſt, but with much content would willingly imbrace it. And whereas the alterations, and begettings of times haue brought forth many notable and famous experiments, vnknowne or aſſayed by our firſt Anceſtors, I haue alſo gathered them together,
<pb facs="tcp:11193:4"/> and ſo made to their excellent grounds the rare di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of latter wits, that the moſt curious ſhall not neede to ſeeke further for any neceſſary knowledge in any of theſe ſeuerall recreations: for hee ſhall learne heereby both abſolutely to doe and ſpeake whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer beſeemes the perſon of ſuch a profeſſor: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as it hath beene gathered with Care, imbrace it with Loue, and I will wiſh thee what I would haue hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen giue mee; The name of a good man.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="1 (hawking)" type="book">
                  <pb facs="tcp:11193:4"/>
                  <head>A Ievvell for Gentrie. <hi>Being an exact Dictionarie, or true</hi> Method, to make any man vnderſtand all <hi>the Art, Secrets, and worthy knowledges</hi> belonging to Hawking, Hunting, Fow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and Fiſhing, together with all the true meaſures for the winding of the Horne.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt, to entreat of Hawkes from their beginnings: Firſt vnderſtand they be Egges, then after they are diſcloſed, Hawkes, but Goſhawkes be commonly diſcloſed as ſoone as Choughes, and in ſome places ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, according to the temperature of the Countrie, and timely brée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. You are to vnderſtand that Hawkes, doe eyrie, and not bréede in Woods: and further, that Hawkes doe draw, when they beare timbring to their neſts, and not that they build, or make their neſts: and in time of their loue, they call, and not kanke, &amp; you muſt ſay that they tread, and when they be vncloſed and begin for to feather any thing of length, by kinde they will draw out of their neſts, and come to the bowes, and come againe to their neſts, and then they be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Boweſſes or Branchers: and after S. <hi>Margarets</hi> day, they flye from trée to trée: and then they are called Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers onely, then it is time for to take them: and ſeuen daies
<pb facs="tcp:11193:5"/> after S. <hi>Margarets</hi> day, is the beſt taking of Sparrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hawkes. Yet there be ſome Faulconers which will take them within ſeauen daies after they be diſcloſed, at which time the white downe is not come from them, nor any pen-feather (except vpon the wings) to be diſcerned, and ſuch Hawkes are called Ieſſes: they be moſt familiar and louing to the man, very ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>y, and not apt by any meanes to be loſt, onely their exceſſiue crying is much troubleſome.</p>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>How you ſhall behaue you in taking of Hawkes, and with what Inſtruments, and how you ſhall Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e them.</head>
                     <p>HE that will take Hawkes, muſt haue Nets which are called Vrines, and thoſe muſt be made of good ſmall thréed, and it muſt be dyed eyther gréene or blew, that they be not eſpied, and you muſt take with you néedle and thréed, to inſéele the Hawkes that are taken, and in this manner they muſt be inſéeled: Take the néedle &amp; thréed and put it through the vpper eye lid, and ſo of the other, and make them faſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the beake that ſhe ſée not: when ſhe is inſéeled, beare her home, and caſt her on the Perch, and let her ſtand there a night and a day, and the next day take and cut the thréed away ſoftly for breaking the eye lids: then gently begin to reclaime her, and deale eaſily with her, til ſhe will ſit vpon thy fiſt, for feare of hurting her wings, and the ſame night after the féeding, wake her all night &amp; all the next day, then ſhe will be eaſie enough to be reclaymed and the firſt meat that ſhe eateth let it be hot, and giue her enough therof. Now there be Faulconers of latter and better knowledge which will not ſéele their young Hawkes at all, but rather Male them, which is leſſe painefull and dangerous to the Hawke, and it is in this manner: you ſhall take an hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kercher, and knitting the two corners together ſo ſtraight that the Hawke can but onely put forth her head, which forcing her to do you ſhall draw the reſt of the handkercher ouer all her bodie, and fold it ſo cloſe about her, that by
<pb facs="tcp:11193:5"/> no meanes ſhe can ſtirre her wings, which done, you may carry her home without any trouble, and there vnmayling her, caſt her on the Perch.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>How your Hawke may be drawne to be reclaimed, and the manner of her dyet.</head>
                     <p>BEfore you caſt your Hawke vpon the Perch, you ſhall put vpon her a Rufter hood, which muſt be wide and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, then by rubbing warme meat vpon her féete, and tickling her ſo as ſhe may looke downeward, and ſometimes by touching her beake with the meat, and then putting it to her féete againe, you ſhall make her learne to féede, which after ſhe hath taken a bite or two ſhe will doe willingly: then you ſhall begin to watch her, and not ſuffer her to take any reſt till ſhe be ſo gentle and patient that ſhe will ſuffer you to take off her hoode, and put it on againe, and will féede bare fac'ſt, without taking any offence or bating: then being hard penned, ſhe may be drawne to be reeclaymed: for while ſhe is tender penned, ſhe is not able to be rclaymed: and if ſhe be a Goſhawke or Tercell that is reclaimed, euer féed her with waſht meat at the drawing, and at the reclaiming, but let it be hot, and in this manner waſh it: Put the meat into the water, and ſtrike it vp and downe in the water, and wring the water out of it, and féede her therewith, if ſhe be a Brauncher: and if it be an Eyes, you muſt waſh it clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner then ye doe to the Brauncher, and with a linnen cloath wipe it and féede her: and euermore the third day when ſhe is flying giue her caſting, and if ſhe be a Goſhawke or Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, in this manner: Take new Blanket cloath, and cut fine morſels, &amp; with a kniues point make a hole in euery morſell, and put in the pellets of cloath, and put them in a faire diſh of water, then take the Hawke and giue her a morſell of hot meat, the quantitie of halfe her ſupper, then take that which lyeth in the water and feede her for all night.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb facs="tcp:11193:6"/>
                     <head>How you ſhall feed your Hawke, and to know her infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, and of the diuerſities of them.</head>
                     <p>IF your Hawke be a Sparhawke, euer féed her with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waſht meate, and looke that her caſting be plumage, then looke it be cleane vnder the Perch, for the next day you ſhall finde her caſting vnder the Perch, and therby you ſhal know whether ſhe be cleane or not: for ſome péeces will bée yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, and ſome gréene, and ſome clammy, and ſome cleare: and if it be yellow ſhe ingendreth the Frounce, which is an euill that will riſe in the mouth, or in the cheeke: and if it be gréene ſhe ingendreth the Rye: the condition of this euill is this, it will ariſe in the head, and make the head ſwel, and the eye wil be heauy and darke, and if it be not holpen it wil fall downe into the legs, and make them ranckle, and if it goe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the head againe, then the Hawke is loſt: if it be clammy the ingendreth an euill called the Cray, which is when ſhe may not mutiſe or mute.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Marke well your Medicines heere following.</head>
                     <p>FOr the Frounce in the mouth, take the ſmall end of a ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſpoone, and put it into the fire, till it be hot, then open the beake and burne the ſore, &amp; annoint it with the marrow of a Gooſe, that hath lyen long, and it will helpe her: if the Frounce be great, then there is a gurb in it, which you muſt cut with a Raſer, hold the Hawke and ſlit the place where the ſore is, and you ſhall finde in it as it were the maw of a Pigeon, take a paire of ſhéeres and ſnip the ſore, and make it as cleane as you can with a linnen cloth, and annoint the ſore foure daies with Balme, and afterwards with Pampilion till it be whole: The Frounce commeth when a man fée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth his Hawke with Porke or Horſe-fleſh foure daies together.</p>
                     <p>For default of hot meat the diſeaſe of the Rye commeth, and the beſt cure therefore is to let her tyre much vpon ſinewic and tough meat, as the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>umps of Mutton, Béefe, or
<pb facs="tcp:11193:6"/> ſuch like, and with the ſame to mingle euer a handfull of Parcelie, that as ſhe teares the meate ſhe may teare it alſo.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>How the Cray commeth.</head>
                     <p>THe Cray commeth of waſht meat, which is waſht with hot water, for lacke of hot meat, &amp; it commeth of thréeds which is in the fleſh that the Hawke is fed with, and though ye picke the fleſh neuer ſo cleane, ye ſhall finde thréeds ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. And the beſt cure is with a little warme oyle of Roſes to bath and cleanſe her tuell or fundament, and then to giue her the ſcowring of Selladine rootes dipt in Oyle of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes alſo.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>When your Hawke ſhall bathe her.</head>
                     <p>EVery third day let your Hawke bathe her during Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, if it be faire weather, &amp; once in a wéeke in Winter, if it be warme, and not elſe, and when you bath your Hawke euer giue her ſome hot meat vnwaſhed, although ſhe bee a Goſhawke, and the beſt hot meate is Sparrowes or other ſmall birds, and next them the Pigeon, Rooke, or Chicken.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>How you ſhall make your Hawke flye with a good courage in the morning.</head>
                     <p>IF you will haue her flye in the morning, feede her the night before with hot meat, and waſh the ſame meat in vrine, and wring out the water cleane, and that will make her haue a luſtie courage to flie after the beſt manner.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>How you ſhall guide your Hawke if ſhe be full gorged, and that you would gladly haue a flight.</head>
                     <p>IF your Hawke be full gorged, and that you would ſpée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily haue her flye, take foure cornes of Wheat, and put them in a morſell of fleſh, and giue it her to eate, and ſhée will quickly caſt all that is within her, and after that ſhe hath caſt, looke that you haue ſome hot meat to giue her.
<pb facs="tcp:11193:7"/> Yet vſe this but ſeldome for feare it bring your Hawke to ſuch a weakeneſſe of ſtomacke that the will not be able to indue any meat at all.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Another medicine for the Rye.</head>
                     <p>TAke D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>e leaues and ſtampe them in a Morter, and wring out the iuyce, &amp; with a pen put it into the Hooke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mares once or twiſe, when the Hawke is ſmall gorged, and anone after let her lyre, and ſhe ſhall be as whole as a fiſh.</p>
                     <p>Alſo, and you giue your Hawke freſh Butter, or Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row of Hogs that is in the bone of the leg of Porke, it will make her caſt water at the mares: but it will make her haughtie and proud.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Another medicine for the Cray.</head>
                     <p>TAke and chafe the fundament of your Hawke with your hand and warme water a good while, and after that take the powder of <hi>Saxifrage,</hi> or elſe the powder of Rew, and a quantitie of May Butter, and temper them well together, then put it in a little Boxe and ſtop it cloſe, and euery meale when you féede your Hawke annoint her meate therewith, and for the loue of the oyntment ſhe will eate her meat the better. This experiment will kéepe her from the Cray, and many other ſickneſſes that oft ingender in Hawkes. Alſo take the whole heart of a Pigge, and féede her therewith two daies, and it will make her whole.</p>
                     <p>Alſo take Porke and put it into hot Milke, and féede your Hawke therwith, and that will make your Hawke mute af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the beſt manner: And Porke, with the Marrow of the Leg of Porke will make her doe the like. Alſo vſe her to freſh Butter &amp; it will doe the ſame. Alſo one or two meales of a Pigs liuer hot will make her mute, but let her not haue too great a gorge thereof, for it is a perillous meat. Alſo take the white of an Egge, and beat it that it be as thin as wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: put the ſame in a veſſell, and ſtéepe the meat there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in all the day before you giue it her, and at night féede her
<pb facs="tcp:11193:7"/> therewith, and that which ſhall be for her dinner the next day, let it lie in ſtéepe all night: but in any wiſe ſée that you haue freſh whites of Egges, and if her féeding be of Porke it is the better. This is proued.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The perfect rules or tearmes for Faulkners, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to Hawkes.</head>
                     <p>THe firſt is hold faſt at all times, and eſpecially when ſhe bateth: it is called bating, for ſhe bateth with her ſelfe moſt often cauſeleſſe. The ſecond is, rebate your Hawke to your fiſt, and that is when your Hawke bateth, the leaſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing that you can make of your fiſt, ſhe wil rebate againe on your fiſt. The third is, ſéede your Hawke, and not giue her meate. The fourth, ſhe ſmiteth or ſeweth her beake, and not wipeth. The fiſt, your Hawke ſouketh, and not ſléepeth. The ſixt, ſhe pruneth, and not perketh: and ſhe pruneth not but when ſhe beginneth at her legs, and fetcheth moyſture like Oyle at her tayle, and bawmeth her feete, and ſtroketh the feathers of her wings through her beake: it is called the Note, when ſhe fetcheth ſuch oyle. A Hawke would neuer be let of her pruning: for when ſhe pruneth her ſelfe ſhe is luſtie and of good liking, and when ſhe hath done ſhe will rowſe her ſelfe mightily: and ſometime ſhe countenanceth as ſhe picketh her, and yet ſhe pruneth her not, and then you muſt ſay ſhe reformeth her feathers, and not picke her fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. The ſeuenth your Hawke collyeth, and not beaketh. The eight rouſeth, and not ſhaketh her. The ninth, ſhe ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth, and not claweth nor ſcratcheth. The tenth, ſhe man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telleth, and not ſtretcheth: when ſhe putteth forth her legs from her, one after another, and her wings follow her legs, then ſhe doth mantell her, and when ſhe hath mantelled and bringeth both her wings together ouer her backe, you muſt ſay ſhe warbleth her wings, and that is a tearme fit for it. The eleuenth, your Hawke muteſſeth, or muteth, and not ſhiteth. The twelfth, you caſt your Hawke vpon the Perch and not ſet her vpon the Perch.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb facs="tcp:11193:8"/>
                     <head>For ſpeciall tearmes belonging to Hawkes, when you ſhall haue any cauſe to commend them for diuers of their properties.</head>
                     <p>FIrſt, you muſt ſay ſhe is a fayre Hawke, a huge Hawke, a long Hawke, a ſhort thicke Hawke: and not to ſay, a great Hawke: Alſo ſhe hath a large beake, or a ſhort beake: and not call it a bill: and a huge head, or a ſmall head, fayre ſeaſoned. You muſt ſay your Hawke is full gorged, and not cropped: and your Hawke putteth ouer and endueth, and yet ſhe doth both diuerſly. You ſhall ſay ſhe is a Hawke of an excellent péece, when her proportion is ſquare and broad betwéene the Pinions, you ſhall ſay ſhe is of a fayre malye, eyther ſandie, blew, or white, which are the extrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt circles or tips of her feathers.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>How your Hawke putteth ouer.</head>
                     <p>SHe putteth ouer when ſhe remoueth her meat from her gorge into her bowels: and thus ye ſhall know: when ſhe hath put it ouer, ſhe trauerſeth with her body, and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cially with her necke, as a Crane doth, or other bird.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>When you ſhall ſay ſhe endueth and embowelleth.</head>
                     <p>SHe neuer endueth ſo long as her bowels be full at her féeding, but as ſoone as ſhe is fed and reſteth, ſhe endueth by little and little: and if her gorge and her bowels in any thing ſtiffeth, you ſhall ſay ſhe is embowelled, and hath not fully endued: and as long as you may find any thing in her bowels, it is very dangerous to giue her any meat.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Marke well theſe tearmes.</head>
                     <p>SAy your Hawke hath a long wing, a faire long taile with ſixe bars out, and ſtandeth vpon the ſeuenth. This Hawk is interpened, that is to ſay, where the feathers of the wings be betwéene the body &amp; thighes: this Hawke hath an huge leg; or a flat leg, or a round leg, or a faire enfered leg.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb facs="tcp:11193:8"/>
                     <head>To know the mayle of an Hawke.</head>
                     <p>HAwkes haue white mayle, Canuas mayle, or red mayle, and ſome call red mayle, yron mayle: which mayle is ſoone knowne. Canuas mayle is betwéene white mayle and yron mayle, and yron mayle is very red.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Plumage and caſt your Hawke.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A</hi> Goſhawke nor Tercel, in their ſore age haue not their mayles named, but is called their plumage: and after that coate it is called their mayle: And if your Hawke flye for, or reward to any Hawke by countenance to flye therto, you ſhall ſay caſt your Hawke thereto, and not flye thereto.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Noumed or ſeaſed.</head>
                     <p>ANd if your Hawke noume a fowle, &amp; the fowle breake from her, ſhe hath diſcomfited many feathers of the fowle, that is broken away: but in kindly ſpéech you ſhall ſay, your Hawke hath noumed or ſeaſed a fowle, &amp; not taken it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Wherefore a Hawke is called a Rifler.</head>
                     <p>OFtentimes it happeneth with a Hawke, that for ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerneſſe when ſhe ſhould noume a Fowle, ſhe ſeaſeth but the feathers, and therefore ſuch Hawkes be called Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flers if they doe oft ſo.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The names of all the members of your Hawkes, with their conuenient tearmes.</head>
                     <p>FIrſt, Cleys behinde that ſtreyneth the backe of the hand, ye ſhall call them Talons.</p>
                     <p>The Cleys within the foot, you ſhall call them her pounſes.</p>
                     <p>But the Cleys that are vpon the middle ſtretchers, you ſhall call them the long ſengles.</p>
                     <p>And the vttermoſt Cleys, you ſhall call them petty ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles, and the leg in generall is called the beame.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb facs="tcp:11193:9"/>
                     <head>The Key or cloſer.</head>
                     <p>THe long ſengles are called the Key of the foot, or the clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer: for what thing ſoeuer a Hawke ſtreineth, is vpon the ſengle, and the ſtrength thereof fortifieth all the foote.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Seres of watery or waxie colours.</head>
                     <p>YOu ſhall vnderſtand, that the ſkinne about the Hawkes legs and her féete, is called the Seres of her legs, and her féete whether they be watry or waxy colour are yellow, yet ſome be more blewiſh or inclining to a ſea-gréene, which is the beſt of all, for it ſheweth valour, and that the Hawke is bred in a hard, cold, and ſtrong Erie.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The beame feathers.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A</hi> Hawke hath twelue feathers on her tayle, and one principal feather of the ſame in the midſt, and in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner all the reſt are couered vnder the ſaid feather, and that is called the beame feather of the tayle, &amp; there is black bars ouerthwart the tayle, and thoſe barres will tell you when ſhe is full ſummed or full fermed: for when ſhe is full barred ſhe ſtandeth vpon ſeauen, and then ſhe is perfect readie to be reclaymed: as long as a Hawke ſtandeth vnder the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of ſeauen barres, and ſhe be in her ſore age, you may ſay ſhe is not full ſummed, for ſo long ſhe is but tender penned, whether ſhe be Brauncher or Eyes: And if ſhe be a mewed Hawke and ſtand within ſeauen barres, you may ſay ſhe is not full fermed, for ſhe is not able to be reclaymed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe is drawne too ſoone out of the mew, for ſhe is not penned no harder then a ſore Hawke: or you ſhall ſay her feathers are in bloud, which is a general warning or caueat that you may in no wiſe draw or reclayme your Hawke till ſhe be hard penned.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Brayles or Brayle-feathers.</head>
                     <p>AN Hawke hath long ſmal white feathers, hanging vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der her tayle from her bowels downeward, and it is
<pb facs="tcp:11193:9"/> called the Brayle-feather: and commonly euery Goſhawke, and euery Tercels brayles be ſprinkled with blacke ſpecks like armines, but for all that, they be accounted neuer the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: But if a Sparrowhawke, be ſo armined vpon the brayles, or any Muſket, you ſhall ſay ſhe is degouted to the vttermoſt brayle, and it betokeneth great hardneſſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Breaſt feathers, Plumage, Barbe feathers, Pendant feathers.</head>
                     <p>THe feathers aboue the former part of a Hawke, be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led breaſt feathers, and the feathers vnder the wings are Plumage: the feathers vnder the beake be called Barbe feathers: the feathers that be at the ioynt of the knée, that are hanging and ſharpe at the ends, thoſe be called the Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant feathers.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Flages or flagge feathers.</head>
                     <p>THe feathers at the wings next to the bodie, be the flages, or flagge feathers.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Beame feathers of the wing.</head>
                     <p>THe long feather of the wing is called the Beame fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the feather that ſome call the pinion of other fowles, of an Hawke it is called a ſercell: and if ſhe be in mew, the ſame feather will be the laſt that ſhe will caſt, and till that be caſt ſhe is neuer mewed. I haue heard ſome ſay that ſhe hath caſt that firſt, but the other rule is more common: and when ſhe hath caſt her ſercel in mew, then is it time to féed her with waſht meat, &amp; to begin to enſayme her.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Enſayme.</head>
                     <p>ENſayme of an Hawke is the greace, and if that be taken away with féeding of waſht meate (as it is declared hereafter) ſhe will gender a panell, which will be her vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter confuſion, if ſhe flye therewith and take cold there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon: for indéede it is onely moderate and temperate exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe which beſt enſaymeth a Hawke, for that breaketh
<pb facs="tcp:11193:10"/> and diſſolueth the greaſe moſt naturally, which afterward you muſt force her to auoid by gentle ſcourings, and after taking of ſtones and caſting, the one being an excellent cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, and the other a moſt perfect cleanſer of the gorge and other vncleane places where the glut remaineth.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Couerts, or couert feathers.</head>
                     <p>THere be feathers vpon the Sercelles, and thoſe be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led couert-feathers, and ſo all the feathers be called that be next ouer the beame feathers, or the flagge feathers of the wings: the foremoſt out-bearing feathers of a Hawke are called the breſt feathers, the feathers vnder the wings are called plumage, thoſe vnder the beake are called the barbe feathers, and thoſe which are at the ioynt of the Hawkes knée, hanging downeward, be called the pendant feathers.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Backe feathers.</head>
                     <p>THe feathers vpon the backe, halfe be called backe fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Beake, Clap, Nares, Sere.</head>
                     <p>THe Beake of the Hawke is the vpper part that is crée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked: the neither part is called the Clap of the Hawke: the holes in the Hawkes beake be called the Nares: the yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low betwéene the beake and the eye is called the Sere.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Cryuets.</head>
                     <p>THere be long ſmall blacke feathers like haires about the Seres, and thoſe be called Cryuets of the Hawke.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Sore age.</head>
                     <p>YOu ſhall vnderſtand that the firſt yéere of an Hawke, whether ſhe be a Brancher or Eyeſſe, the firſt is called her ſore age, and all that yéere ſhe is called a ſore Hawke: and if ſhe eſcape that yéere, with good féeding ſhe is like to endure long, and then ſhe is called an Entermewer: the
<pb facs="tcp:11193:10"/> third yéere ſhe is a white Hawke, the fourth a white Hawke of the firſt coate, and ſo doubling till her end.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>To reclayme a Hawke.</head>
                     <p>IF you will reclayme your Hawke, you muſt diuide one meale into thrée, vntill that ſhe will come to reclayme: and when ſhe will come to reclayme, make her that ſhe ſore not, nor plane: for though ſhe be well reclaymed, it may fall out that ſhe will ſore ſo high, that ye ſhall neuer ſée nor find her: And if your Hawke flye to the Partrich, looke that ye enſayme her before ſhe flye, whether ſhe be a Brauncher, Eyeſſe, or mued Hawke.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>When a Hawke is called an Eyeſſe.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A</hi> Hawke that is called an Eyeſſe, is for her eyen: for a Hawke that is brought vp vnder a Buzard or Put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tocke, (as many are) haue watry eyne: for when they be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed and kept in forme till they be full ſummed, ye ſhall know that by her watry eyes, and alſo her looke will not be ſo quicke as a Braunchers is: and ſo becauſe the beſt know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is by the eye, they be called Eyeſſe: ye may know an Eyeſſe by the paleneſſe of the Seres of her legs, or the ſere ouer the becke: alſo by the taintes that be vpon her tayle and her wings: which taintes come for lacke of féeding when they be Eyeſſes. This is an other opinion of Eyeſſes but that which is formerly declared is moſt vſuall, common and ofteſt within our practiſe, for in theſe latter daies, of better knowledge, men will not ſo miſpend the egs of good Hawkes as to ſuffer them to be diſcloſed by Buzards, or any vnworthy fowles.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>What a Taynt is.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A</hi> Taynt is a thing that goeth ouerthwart the feathers of the wings and of the tayle, like as it were eaten with wormes, and it beginneth firſt to bréed at the bodie in the pen, and the ſame pen ſhall fret a ſunder, and fall
<pb facs="tcp:11193:11"/> away through the ſame Taynt, and then is the Hawke deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paraged for all that yéere.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Medicines to Enſayme your Hawke.</head>
                     <p>TAke the roote of Raſne, and put it in cleane water, and lay your fleſh therein to temper a great while, and giue it to your Hawke to eate: and if ſhe eate thereof, dread not but it will abate her greace, but in thrée daies ſhe will not greatly abate. Alſo take Puliall and Garlicke, and ſtampe it well together, and wring out the iuyce in a diſh and then wet the fleſh therein, and féede your Hawke therewith: Enſayme your Hawke within foure daies, but looke euery day that you make new iuyce, and when you féede her, wet your meat therein: Alſo take iuyce of Marſley mores, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe called Perſley roots, and the ſame of Iſope, and waſh your fleſh therein, and your Hawke ſhall be enſaymed kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and no great abate to the Hawke. Some vſe to lay their fleſh in water almoſt a day, and giue the ſame to the Hawke at ſupper, and let that lie all night to giue her in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and thus to féede them in the mew, or ere they be drawne, about a moneth or ſixe wéekes, and to enſayme them ere they come on the fiſt, and aſſoone as they caſt their ſercell, then is it time to féede them ſo.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>How your Hawke enſaymeth.</head>
                     <p>YOu ſhall further vnderſtand, that ſo long as your Hawkes féete looke blacke and rough, ſhe is ful of greace, and euer as ſhe enſaymeth, her féete will waxe yellow and looke ſmooth.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>How you ſhall behaue your ſelfe when your Hawke is readie to flye.</head>
                     <p>VVHen you haue enſaymed your Hawke and recla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med her, and that ſhe is readie to flye to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trich, you muſt take a Partrich in your bagge and go into the field, and let your Spaniells finde a couie of Partriches, and
<pb facs="tcp:11193:11"/> when they bvp and begin to ſcatter, you muſt marke them and couple vp your Spaniels: and when you haue ſo done, let him that hath the Partri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h in the bagge take a paire of creance to the Partrich legge, and caſt her vp as hie as you can, &amp; as ſoone as your Hawke ſéeth her ſhe will flye thereto: and if your Partrich ſeaſe vpon her aboue, giue her a reward thereupon: this done, goe to the Partriches that you haue marked, doe as hereafter followeth: and if you haue a cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſed Spaniell that is rebuked and is a retriuer, vncouple him alone and go and ſingle out one of the Partriches of the couie, and goe as nigh to the riſing of him as you can, and if your Hawke haue a deſire caſt her to it: and if ſhe take it, then your Hawke is made for that yéere, and of the ſame Partrich that ſhée ſlayeth you muſt thus reward her as followeth. There be other latter Fawlkners which for the making of a young Hawke, will take a Partrich and ſéele it, then com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming into the field, in a place which is both moſt likely for the haunt of Partriches, and alſo moſt conuenient for the making of your ſlight: take the Partrich and lay her downe cloſe in ſome furrow, and couer her with a Hat, ſo as ſhée cannot ſpring vp, then hauing a long line faſtned to the Hat, let one ſtand a farre off from the Hat, and hold the line in his hand, all which when you ſée well prepared, then caſt off your Hawke, and after ſhée hath flowne about or two, ſéeing her head to be turned inward towards the game, you ſhall cauſe him that hath the ſtring to plucke away the Hat, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which diſcouerie the Partrich will ſpring, and the Hawke will ſtoope and purſue it, which aſſoone as ſhe hath taken, you ſhall very well reward her vpon it, as with the head, necke, intrailes, and at the leaſt one of the legges, onely you muſt remember, that before you giue your Hawke this traine, you muſt make her very willing to foote any hand Partrich whatſoeuer.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb facs="tcp:11193:12"/>
                     <head>How you ſhall reward your Hawke.</head>
                     <p>TAke the Partrich, and cut the head and necke from the body, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> the ſkinne from the necke, and giue it her to eate, and couer the body of the Fowle with a hat, and lay the ſayd head and the necke thereupon, and if ſhee will forſake the Fowle that ſhe plumeth on and come to the reward, then ſecretly take away the Partrich, and reward your Hawke with the braine and the necke, but beware that ſhe eate no bones, for it will make her vnluſtie for to flye: and thus muſt you ſerue her of as many as ſhe flyeth at, but let her reward be the leſſe, or elſe ſhe will be quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly full gorged, and then ſhe will not flye a good while.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>How your Hawke ſhall reioyce her ſelfe.</head>
                     <p>VVHen your Hawke hath ſlaine a Fowle, and that you haue rewarded her as before, let her flye no more till ſhe hath reioyced her: that is to ſay, till ſhe hath ſewed, feakt, or ſnited her beake, or elſe rouzed her: and when ſhe hath done any of all theſe, goe and retriue more, and ſhe will noume plentie.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>When your Hawke hath noumed a Fowle, what you ſhall doe that you rebuke not the Hawke.</head>
                     <p>LEarne this thing when ſhe doth noume a Fowle, ſtand good way from her, and take away your Spanieles for rebuking of her, for diuers Hawkes con not abide the Spaniels, and when your Hawke plumeth, come ſoftly to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards her néerer and néerer, and if ſhe leaue pluming &amp; looke vpon you: ſtand ſtil and chearke her and wiſtell her, vntill ſhd plume againe, and ſerue her thus vntill you be nigh her, then ſoftly fall on your Knées, and priuily while ſhée plumeth, ſet your hand, and be ſure of the Ieſſe, and then ye may guide all things as you will, and if you doe the contrarie, ſhée will for feare carrie away the game, or let it goe quicke, which is loſſe both to you and to your Hawke alſo. Beſides, raſh
<pb facs="tcp:11193:12"/> comming in to a Hawke, maketh her take diſlike at a mans face and countenance, and that toy once conceiued, ſhe will neuer after indure to looke vpon him at libertie, as we dayly ſée by experience of many good Hawkes at this day, from whom the beſt Fawlkners cannot take away that infirmitie: therefore the ſafeſt way of preuention, is to doe nothing about her raſhly, but with great temperance and a countenance chearfull, and amiable.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>A Medicine for an Hawke that is lowſie.</head>
                     <p>TAke quickſiluer, and put it into a Baſon of Braſſe, and put into it Salindine and Aſhes, and mingle it well to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether till the quickſiluer be dead, &amp; put thereto fat of bones, and annoynt the Hawke therewith, and it will kill the Lice: alſo powder of Orpement blowne vpon the Hawke with a quill will kill the Lice.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The opinion of Oſtregiors.</head>
                     <p>AFter the opinion of many Oſtregiors, if you féede your Hawke continually with Porke, with Iayes or Pyes, or carrie her much in raynie weather, ſhe will be lowſie.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Oſtregers, Speruiters, Faulkners.</head>
                     <p>BEcauſe I ſpake of Oſtregers, you ſhall vnderſtand that they be called Oſtregers that kéepe Goſhawkes or Tercels of Goſhawkes, and thoſe that kéepe Sparrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hawkes and Muſkets, be called Speruiters, and kéepers of all other Hawkes be called Faulkners.</p>
                     <p>You ſhall call the long Line wherewith you call your Hawke, your Creance, whatſoeuer it be.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>A medicine for an Hawke that caſteth her fleſh.</head>
                     <p>PVt the fleſh that you féede your Hawke withall in faire water, and féede her therewith thrée daies, and it will kéepe her in fleſh.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb facs="tcp:11193:13"/>
                     <head>A medicine for an Hawke that hath loſt her courage.</head>
                     <p>YOu may know when your Hawke hath loſt her cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, for when you caſt her to the Fowle: ſhe flyeth awayward, as though ſhe knew not the Fowle, or elſe ſhe will flye a little after her, and then giue her vp: and this is a very good remedie for ſuch a Hawke. Take Oyle of Spaine, and temper it with cleare Wine and the yolke of an Egge, and put into it ſome Beefe, and giue her there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of fiue morſels, and then ſet her in the Sunne, and at night féede her with an old hot Culuer, and if you féede her thus thrée times: your Hawke was neuer ſo luſty and iolly before, as ſhe will be after, and come to her courage againe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>A Medicine that an Hawke ſhall not lye in Mew for vnluſtineſſe.</head>
                     <p>TAke Fearne roots that grow within an Oke, and Oke apples, and make iuyce of them, and wet her fleſh therein that ſhe eateth, and féede her thrée or foure times, and it will make her leaue that.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>A Medicine for an Hawke that hath the Tanie.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A</hi> Hawke that hath the Tanie, a man may ſoone know if he take héede: for this is her manner, ſhe will pant more for one baiting then ſome will doe for thrée or foure, and if ſhe ſhould flye a little while, ſhe would almoſt loſe her breath: whether ſhe be fat or leane, and ſhe will be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies heauie, and this is the remedie. Take a quantitie of the redneſſe of Haſell, and a little of the powder of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, of Pepper, and ſomewhat of Ginger, and make there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of with freſh greace three pellets, and hold your Hawke to the fire, and when ſhe féeleth the heate, make her ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the thrée pellets by force, and knit her beake faſt that ſhe caſt it not out againe, and this doe thrée times, and ſhe ſhall be ſafe.</p>
                     <p>Alſo take Aliſander, and the Roots of Primroſes, and the
<pb facs="tcp:11193:13"/> roote Grongnaulles, and ſéeth them in Butter, and giue her thrée morſels euery day, vntill ſhe be whole, and looke that ſhe be empty when ye giue the medicine.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>How you ſhall take your Hawke from the Erye.</head>
                     <p>VVHo ſo taketh his Hawke from the Erye, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houeth him to be wiſe in bringing her eaſily, and to kéepe her from cold, and from hurting of her bones, for they be tender, and ſhe muſt haue great reſt, and they muſt haue as cleane ayre as can be, and alwaies giue her cleane and hot meate, and giue her a little and often, and chaunge her meate often, and cut her meate into ſmall morſels, for they ſhould not tyre on bones: and then when ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth to pen, and plumeth, and pruneth, and picketh her ſelfe, put her into a cloſe warme place where no Vermine may come in to her, and let the place be cloſe from winde and rayne, and then ſhe will ſome her ſelfe: and euermore giue her good hot meates, for it is better for a man to féede his Hawke while ſhe is tender with good meate, and to make her good with ſome coſt, then to féede her with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill meates to make her vnthriftie with little coſt: and looke when ſhe beginneth to ſome, then giue her bathing.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>A Medicine for wormes in a Hawke, which ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is called the Fylanders.</head>
                     <p>BEware of this ſickeneſſe: the remedie for it is this. Take an herbe that is called Neppe, and put it into the gut of a Capon, or of an Hen, and knit it with a thréed, and let her receiue it whole, and ſhe will be whole and ſafe.</p>
                     <p>Thus you ſhall know when your Hawke hath wormes in her belly: looke when ſhe hath caſt, and then ye ſhall finde one or two about her caſting place, if ſhe hath within her any.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb facs="tcp:11193:14"/>
                     <head>A Medicine for an Hawke that caſteth wormes at her fundament, and what wormes they be.</head>
                     <p>TAke the lymayle of yron, and mingle it with the fleſh of Porke, and giue it two daies to the Hawke to eate, and ſhe ſhall be whole.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>A Medicine for an Hawke that hath a ſickneſſe called the Aggerſteyne.</head>
                     <p>VVHen you ſée your Hawke hurt her féete with her beake, and pulleth her tayle, then ſhe hath the Ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerſteyne: For this diſeaſe, take the dung of a Doue, and the dung of a Shéepe, and ſtrong Vineger, and mingle them ſoftly in a brazen baſon, and mingle them welll together to ſerue for thrée daies after, and giue her fleſh of a Culuer with Honey, and with powder of Pepper, and ſet her in a darke place nine dayes, and when you ſée new feathers on her tayle, waſh her with Veroſe nine daies, and ſhe will be whole.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>A Medicine for an Hawke that hath the Crampe in her wings, and how it commeth.</head>
                     <p>TAke a white Loafe of bread, ſomewhat colder then it comes out of the Ouen, and hold the Hawke ſoftly for hurting, and cut the Loafe almoſt through, and diſplay her wing eaſily, and hold it betwéene the two parts of the Loafe, and let it be held ſo the ſpace of halfe an houre, and it will helpe her.</p>
                     <p>The Crampe commeth to an Hawke by taking cold in her youth: therefore it is good for an Hawke to kéepe her warme, whether ſhe be young or old.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Let not your Hawke be put into mewe to fat, but in this manner as followeth, if ye loue her.</head>
                     <p>KEepe her well, and put her not late in mew: for who ſo for couetouſnes of flying, loſeth the time of his Hawkes mewing, and with-holdeth her too long from it, he may after
<pb facs="tcp:11193:14"/> put her in mew at aduenture, for then a part of her mewing time is paſt. Who ſo putteth his Hawke in mew in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of Lent, if ſhe be kept as ſhe ought to be, ſhe ſhould be mewed in the beginning of Auguſt, which is the beſt time of all other.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>How you ſhall diſpoſe and ordaine your mew.</head>
                     <p>SEt and diſpoſe your mew in this manner, ſo that no We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell nor Pole<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t, nor no other Vermine annoy it, nor that it be windie or cold, nor that it be ouer hot, let one part of it ſtand towards the Sunne, ſo that the moſt part of the day the Sunne may come to it Alſo you muſt looke that ſhe be not troubled with noyſe or the ſinging of men, &amp; that no man come to her but onely he that féedeth her: you muſt let her haue a féeding ſtocke in her mew, and a long ſtring to binde her meate, or elſe ſhe will carry her meat about the houſe and beray it with duſt, and peraduenture ſhe will hide it till it ſtinke and then féede on it: which if ſhe ſhould do, it would be her death. And therefore when it is bound to the féeding ſtocke, then ſhe will neyther at féeding, neyther at tyring, nor at lighting downe, nor at riſing hurt her ſelfe: and when ſhe hath fed, take away that ſhe leaueth, and looke that ſhe haue freſh at euery meale: for of ſtale and euill meats ſhe will ingender many diſeaſes, and looke that you neuer go to the mew but when you carry her meat or water to bath her. Suffer no rayne to wet her at any time if you may: and as for her bathing, that will nothing hinder her mewing. This mew would notwithſtanding the warmth and cloſeneſſe, haue a conuenient place from ſome window built aboue a yard outward, and at leaſt a yeard and a halfe ſquare, which would be onely lathed of an indifferent wideneſſe without any loome, ſo as the ayre might fréely come in thereat, for this muſt be the place where your Hawke in the heate of Summer may weather her ſelfe, which is as comfortable as any meat whatſoeuer: Beſides your mew muſt neuer be without ſtore of Hawkes ſtones of all fiſes, of ſand, grauell
<pb facs="tcp:11193:15"/> and gréene tuffes, for it is both wholeſome and naturall for a Hawke to féede vpon the gréene graſſe, yet they muſt be often changed, and ſo muſt the water in which ſhe batheth, the tubbe being large and not aboue fiue inches in depth at the moſt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The manner how a man ſhall put his Hawke into the Mew: and is proued.</head>
                     <p>ONe thing you muſt beware of, that ſhe haue no ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe before you put her in Mew: for as I haue proued, a ſicke Hawke ſhall neuer mew well, but though ſhe mew ſhe ſhall not endure: but when ſhe is great and fat, for at the bating of her eſtate, ſhe will no longer endure. Sometime without any medicine many men deuiſe how they may mew their Hawkes: for ſome put them in at high eſtate, &amp; ſome when they be very low, and ſome when they are empty and leane: but it makes no matter for that, if ſhe be ſound: neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe, you ſhal heare mine aduiſe as I haue ſéene &amp; proued.</p>
                     <p>Whoſoeuer putteth a Goſhawke, a Tercell, Sparhawke or any other Hawke into Mew, ſo high that ſhe may be no higher, ſhe will hold her long ere ſhe léeſe and leaue any feathers: and who ſo putteth her into mew, leane, it will be long ere ſhe remount: and who ſo putteth her into mew too leane and hungry, if ſhe haue meate at her will, ſhe will eate too much, becauſe of hunger, and ſhe is likely to kill her ſelfe therewith, as hath béene often ſéene: but who ſo will haue his Hawke indure and mew kindly, my counſel is that ſhe be neither too high nor too low, nor in diſtreſſe of hunger, but as ſhe ſhould beſt flie: but take héede the firſt day of too much eating, till the time that ſhe be ſtanche, and after you may giue her ſuch meat as I ſhall deſcribe you hereafter.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>In what manner you ſhall feede your Hawke in your mew.</head>
                     <p>LOoke what meate ſhe hath béene moſt vſed to be fed with, and féede her therewith eight dayes together, and
<pb facs="tcp:11193:15"/> giue her Birds enough morning and euening, and let her plume vpon them well, and take caſting of the plumage, and that will clenſe her well, and cauſe her to haue good appetite, and it will clenſe her bowelles well, and when ſhe is well clenſed, you may giue her what meate you will, ſo it be cleane and freſh. But the beſt meate to make her mewe ſooneſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any medicine, is the fleſh of a Kid, of a young Swanne, and of a young Chicken, and of a young Gooſe: for ſuch meate is hot of it ſelfe: a Rat alſo is excellent.</p>
                     <p>Alſo take péeces of great freſh Eeles, and eſpecially that next the nauell, and wet it in hot blood of Mutton, it is good to make her to mew, but eſpecially it will make her white after her ſore age. Theſe ſaid fleſhes be good to mew a Hawke, and to kéepe her in ſtate, but looke that ſhe haue plentie eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day, that ſhe rather leaue then lacke, and euery third day let her bathe if ſhe will: and when ſhe is waxed nere ſomed, then let her eate Hennes and fat Porke: and of a Hound is paſſing good. For to ſpeake the truth, and as long experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence teacheth vs, there is no meate generally ſo good for a Hawke that is in any good and perfect ſtate of body, as doggs fleſh is, ſo it be giuen warme or not too ſtale.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>To make a Hawke mew quickly, without any hurting of her.</head>
                     <p>THe experiment is thus approued. Take an Adder that is red of nature, and alſo there be Snakes of the ſame kinde, and they be very bitter, take two or thrée of them, and ſmite off their heads and their tayles: then take a new earthen Pot that was neuer vſed, and cut them in ſmall pée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and put them into the Pot to ſéeth, and let them ſéeth at leiſure, and let the Pot be couered cloſe that no ayre come out of it, nor no breth, and let them ſéeth ſo long that the péeces turne to greace, and put it into a cleane veſſell, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> as oft as you féede your Hawke, annoynt her meat there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, and let her eate as much as ſhée will, and that will mew her at your will.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11193:16"/>
                     <p>Alſo if you take Wheate and Barly and boyle it in the broth that the Adders were ſodden in, and when you ſée it begin to breake, take it out, and féede Henns and Chickens there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, and with thoſe hennes or chicknes féede your Hawke. This medicine is well approued amongſt all our late Faulkners.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Who ſo would haue his Hawke mew, and that her feathers ſhoud not fall.</head>
                     <p>TAke powder of Canel, and the iuyce of Francke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſte, and the iuyce of Paranie, &amp; take thrée or foue mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of meat, and wet them therein, and make your Hawke ſwallowe them, and ſerue her ſo many times.</p>
                     <p>Alſo take the ſkinne of a Snake and of an Adder, and cut them into ſmall péeces, and temper it with hot blood, and make your Hawke to eat thereof, and ſhe ſhall not mew.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>For the Gowte in the throte.</head>
                     <p>VVHen you ſée your Hawke blow many times, and that it commeth of no bating, you may bée ſure ſhe hath the Gowt in her throte: and for that diſeaſe, take the blood of an Peacocke, Incenſe, Myrabolana, &amp; cloue Gil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly flowers and Canel, and Ginger: and take of all theſe euery euening, and mingle them with Peacockes blood, and ſéeth it till they be thicke, and thereof make morſells, and giue the Hawke at morning and noone.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>For the Gowte in the head and in the reynes.</head>
                     <p>VVHen you ſée your Hawke may not endue her meate, nor remoue her eſtate, ſhe hath the Gowte in the head and in the reynes. Take Momie, (among the Apothecaries you may haue it,) and the ſkinne of an Hare, and giue it to your Hawke to eate nine times with the fleſh of a Cat, and if ſhe hold the meate ſhe ſhall be ſafe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb facs="tcp:11193:16"/>
                     <head>A medicine for the Crampe in the thigh, in the legge, or in the foote or an Hawke.</head>
                     <p>VVHen you ſée your Hawke lay one foot vpon an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then ſhe is taken with the Crampe, then draw her blood, both vpon the foote that lyeth on the other foote, and vpon the legge, and it will helpe her.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>For the Cough, or the Poſe.</head>
                     <p>TAke powder of Bayes, and put it on the fleſh of a Doue, and giue it oft to your Hawke, and it will helpe her.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>A medicine for the ſickneſſe within the body of any Hawke, if it ſhew not outwards, how ſhe ſhall be holpen and in what manner.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A</hi> Man may know by the countenance of an Hawke partly her infirmities: but it is ſtraunge to know ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diſeaſes, when he knoweth not whereof nor how it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth: For this deſeaſe féede your Hawke well of an Hen, and then make her faſt two dayes after, that ſhe may emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie her body: the third day take Hony and ſéeth it, and fill her full, and binde her beake that ſhe caſt it not out againe, and then ſet her out of the Sunne, and when it draweth to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards night féede her of a hote Fowle: and if this will not helpe her, neuer looke for other medicine.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>For the paſsion that Goſhawkes haue faſting.</head>
                     <p>TAke the roote of ſmall Ruſhes, and make iuyce of them, and wet her meate therein, and make her eate thereof.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>A medicine for the Falera.</head>
                     <p>VVHen you ſee your Hawkes Tallents waxe white, then it is a ſigne ſhée hath the Falera, the cure is: take a blacke Snake and cut away the head and taile, then take the middle and frie it in an earthen Pot, then take the Greaſe and ſaue it, and annoynt the fleſh either of
<pb facs="tcp:11193:17"/> Pigeon or Hen therewith, and let the Hawke féede thereon eight dayes together: and at the end of eight dayes, féede her with warme Birds.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>For the Podagree.</head>
                     <p>VVHen your Hawkes féete are ſwelled, then we ſay ſhe hath the Podagrée: the cure whereof is, take freſh May Butter, and as much of Oyle Oliue, and of Allome, and chaſe them well together at the fire, and make thereof an oyntment, and annoynt her féete foure dayes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and ſet her in the Sunne, and giue her the fleſh of a Cat, and if you ſée it auaile not, ſéeth the cutting of a Viue and wrap in it about the ſwelling, and let her ſit vpon a cold ſtone, and annoyt her with Butter till ſhe be whole.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>For Hawkes that be wounded.</head>
                     <p>TAke away the feathers about the wound, and take the white of an Egge, and Oyle of Oliue, and mingle them together, and annoynt the wound, and kéepe it with white wine, vntill the time that you ſée dead fleſh, and then put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the wound Eſcompe, vntill the time that the dead fleſh be waſted: after take Incenſe, and take as much of the one as of the other, and mingle them together and when you will annoynt the ſore, heat your oyntment, and annoynt it with a pen, till the time the ſkinne growe againe: and if you ſée dead fleſh about it, and that you would haue it away, waſh it with Vineger, and then annoynt it with this oyntment a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, and ſhe ſhall be whole.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>A medicine for an Hawke that hath the Arteticke.</head>
                     <p>VVHen you perceiue that your Hawke is fat about the heart, you may truſt to it ſhe hath the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teticke, therefore let her blood in the originall vaine, and after that, giue her a Frogge to eate, and ſhe will be whole.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb facs="tcp:11193:17"/>
                     <head>A Medicine for an Hawke that is troubled in the bowels.</head>
                     <p>VVHen your Hawke is troubled in her bowels, you ſhall know it by her eyes, for her eyes will bée darke, and ſhe will looke drowſily, and her mutiſing will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>file her fundament, then take the Hawkes meate, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynt it with the powder of Camomile or Ferne, and giue it her to eate, and ſhe ſhall be whole.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>A Medicine for an Hawke that hath the Gout.</head>
                     <p>FEede your Hawke once or twice with an Irchin, and it ſhall helpe her.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>A Medicine for an Hawke that hath Mytes.</head>
                     <p>TAke the iuyce of Wormewood, and put it where they be, and they will die.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>A Medicine for an Hawke that hath the Stone.</head>
                     <p>ANnoynt her Fundament with Oyle, and put in the powder of Allome with a hollow ſtraw into her fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dament: Alſo take an herbe called Caſtis Larder, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynt her mouth therewith, and ſhe will be whole. Alſo if you take ſmall Flamis roots, and Polepodie of the Oake, and the Nerues of Spinage, and grinde them well, and féeth it in Butter, and ſtrayne it through a cloath, then make thrée Pellets as bigge as a Haſſell Nut, and put them in your Hawkes mouth in the morning, and looke that ſhe be emptie, and then let her faſt till euening, then féede her by little and little till ſhe be ſound.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>A Medicine for Vermin.</head>
                     <p>TAke the iuyce of the roote Fennell, and put it where the Vermin be, and they will die, or if you bathe her in a decoction thereof, it is the ſurer way.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb facs="tcp:11193:18"/>
                     <head>A Medicine for the Rewme that Hawkes haue.</head>
                     <p>VVHen you ſée your Hawke cloſe her eyes, and ſhake her head, giue her Lard of a Goat the firſt day, and the ſecond day giue her Epaticke, with the fleſh of a Chic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and ſhe ſhall be whole.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>A Medicine for Hawkes that be drie and deſire to drinke, to keepe them moyſt.</head>
                     <p>TAke the iuyce of Horehound, and wet the Hawkes meate therein, and féede her therewith once or twice, and ſhe ſhall be whole.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>A Medicine for diſeaſes in the Entrayles.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A</hi> Hawke whoſe intrayles are payned is more then or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily ſicke, for if ſhe hold not her meate but caſt it, it is a token of a foule glut or ſurfait of feathers taken in her ſore-age, and appeares when ſhe comes to much labour: the ſignes are, ſhe will haue much deſire to reſt, and will ſléepe when ſhe putteth ouer her meate, and the fleſh which ſhe hath in her gorge, if ſhe caſt it, lookes as it were ſodden: ſhe will many times aſſay to put ouer her meate but cannot, wherefore if ſhe caſt it ſhe may be holpen, if not, ſhe dieth: The cure therefore is to take the yolkes of Egges rawe, when they be well beaten together, put to it Spaniſh Salt, and as much Honey, and wet therein the Hawkes meate, and féede her therewith thrée dayes toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: and if ſhe make daintie in eating of it, then make her of force to ſwallow thrée or foure morſels a day, and preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhe ſhall be whole. Yet I will tell you another thing: Take Honey at the chaunge of the Moone, and a ſharpe Nettle, and make thereof ſmall powder, and when it is well ground, take the breaſt bone of an Hen, and another of a Culuer, and make it ſmall with a knife, and doe away the ſkinne, and put powder thereon, and all hot with the powder, féede her thrée daies and ſhe will be whole.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb facs="tcp:11193:18"/>
                     <head>For ſickneſſe of ſwelling.</head>
                     <p>IF a Fellon be ſwolne in ſuch ſort that a man may heale it, then thus a man may helpe her and lengthen her life, but the Hawke will be very eager &amp; grieuous of ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: therefore you muſt take the rootes of Comferye and of Suger as much, then ſéeth it in freſh greaſe, with the third part of Honey, and then draw it through a faire cloath, and then oft giue it to the Hawke, and ſhe ſhall be whole.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>A Medicine for Blaynes in Hawkes mouthes, called Frounces.</head>
                     <p>THe Frounce is a fearefull diſeaſe, and draweth her to death, and with-holdeth her ſtrength, and it commeth of cold: for cold doth a Hawke much harme. To cure her, take Fennell, Mariall and Kerſes alike much, and ſéeth them, and ſtraine them through a cloath, and ſomtimes waſh her head therwith, and put ſome on the roofe of her mouth, &amp; ſhe ſhalbe ſafe, otherwiſe for the moſt ſureſt way to cure any Frounce in generall, for indéed they be no other then common Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers in the mouth, ingendred by extreame heats and foule fée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: you ſhal take Allome &amp; bray it into a very fine powder: then mixe it with the ſtrongeſt wine-Vineger, and make it as thicke as Puddle, then with a fine Cambricke rag dipt therein, rubbe the ſore till it bléede, and ſo continue till the Canker be kild, and that the fleſh looke red and cleare, then heale it with a little life-Honey.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>A Medicine for an Hawke that caſteth her fleſh.</head>
                     <p>SEeth Rayſons in water and wet her fleſh therein when it boyleth.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>A Medicine for the Agrum.</head>
                     <p>WHen you ſée your Hawke haue blobed chéekes, then ſhe hath this diſeaſe called Agrum: therefore take a Néedle of Siluer, and heate it in the fire, and burne the Narres throughout, then annoynt it with oyle Oliue.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb facs="tcp:11193:19"/>
                     <head>A Medicine to make a Hawke fat.</head>
                     <p>TAke a quantitie of Porke and Honey, and Butter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like much, and clarified greaſe, take away the Skinne, ſéeth them together, and annoynt the fleſh therewith, and ſhe will encreaſe excéedingly.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>For botches that grow in a Hawkes iaw.</head>
                     <p>CVt the botches with a Knife, and let out the matter, and clenſe it with a ſiluer Spoone, or elſe fill the hole with the powder of Arne Melit, burned into powder, &amp; vpon the powder doe a little cloath beſpred with hot waxe, and ſo it will away.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>A Medicine for an Hawke that will not come to reclayme.</head>
                     <p>TAke freſh Butter, and put into it Suger, and put it in a cleane cloath, and reclayme her to that, and kéepe it in a boxe, and put it into your bagge.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>A Medicine for Hawkes that be refrayned.</head>
                     <p>VVHen you ſée your Hawke to Néeſe, and to caſt water thorow her Noſtriles, then doubleſſe ſhée is refrayned: for this diſeaſe take the graynes of Shaffel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grée, and of Pepper, and grinde it well and temper it with ſtrong Vineger, and put it to the roofe of her mouth, and giue her fleſh to eate, and ſhe ſhall be whole.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>A Medicine for Hawkes that haue paynes in their Croppes.</head>
                     <p>TAke faire Morfumum, and powder of Gilouer, and mingle them together and giue it her to eate, and if ſhée hold it paſt the ſecond day after, ſhe ſhall be whole.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb facs="tcp:11193:19"/>
                     <head>A Medicine for the Stone in the fundament.</head>
                     <p>VVHen your Hawke cannot mute, then ſhe hath this diſeaſe called the Stone: and for this ſickeneſſe you ſhall take the heart of a Swine, and the greaſe of a Swine, and cut it with the fleſh of the heart, and ſhe ſhall be whole.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>A Medicine for the drie Frounce.</head>
                     <p>FOr this ſickneſſe, take the roote of Polipode that grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vpon Okes, and ſéeth it a great while, then take it from the fire, and let it ſtand till it be luke-warme, then waſh your Hawkes fleſh therein thrée times when you féed her, and it will helpe her.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>A Medicine for wormes called Anguellis.</head>
                     <p>TAke preſſure of a Lambe that was eyned before his time, and make thereof thrée morſels, and put it into the gut of a Culuer, and féede her therewith, &amp; looke that the Hawke be emptie when you giue her the Medicine, or elſe take the iuyce of Dragons and fill the gut of a Pigeon, and then cut it as the Hawke may ſwallow it, and knit his beake for caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it vp againe, and giue her the douſſets of a Bucke as hot as they be cut out, and make powder of the piſſell, and caſt it vpon the fleſh, and ſhe ſhall be whole.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Proper tearmes vſed in keeping of Hawkes.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A</hi> Hawke tyreth vpon Rumps, ſhe féedeth vpon all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of fleſh, ſhe gorgeth when ſhe filleth her gorge with meate, ſhe beaketh when ſhe wipeth her beake, ſhe rouſeth when ſhe ſhaketh all her feathers, and her body together, ſhe endueth when her meate in her bowels fals to diſgeſtion, ſhe muteth when ſhe auoids her or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure, ſhe percheth when ſhe ſtandeth on any Bough or Perch, ſhee Ioyketh when ſhée ſléepes, ſhe puts ouer when ſhe auoids her meat out of her gorge into her pannell,
<pb facs="tcp:11193:20"/> ſhe pruneth when ſhe fetcheth Oyle with her beake out of her taile, and annoynts her feathers. She plumeth when ſhe pulleth off the feathers of any Fowle, or any thing, and caſteth it from her: ſhe warbleth when ſhe draweth her winges ouer the midſt of her backe, and ſoftly ſhaketh them, and letteth them fall againe: ſhe mantelleth when ſhe ſtretcheth out one wing alone, and afterward the other wing, and moſt commonly ſhée doth that before ſhée warb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth her.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The names of Sparhawkes, as <hi>Ostregers</hi> and <hi>Speruiters</hi> haue determined.</head>
                     <p>THere is a queſtion aſked whether a man ſhall call a Spere or a Sparhawke, or an Aſper Hawke, and <hi>Oſtregers</hi> and <hi>Speruiters</hi> ſay, ſhée may be called all thrée names: for theſe reaſons, ſhe may be called a Sparrehawke, for of all Hawkes that are, ſhe is moſt ſpere, that is to ſay, moſt ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to kéepe: For the leaſt miſdieting and euill tending of her, killeth her, and ſhe may be called an Aſper Hawke of ſharpnes of her courage, and of her looking quicke, and alſo of her flying. For ſhe is moſt aſpere and ſharp in all things that belong vnto her. Of all Hawkes ſhe may be called a Sparehawke, for two reaſons: one is, ſhe ſpareth Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hawkes &amp; Tercels vntill the time they be reclaimed to flye, and till they be fully mewed and cleane enſaymed, for all the while they be vnable, the Sparhawke occupieth that ſeaſon, &amp; flieth the Partrich wall, from Saint Margarets day vntill it be Lammas, and ſhe will ſley young Feaſants, Hichcokes in the beginning of the yéere: and I haue ſéene them ſlay the Teale, the black bird, the Woodcocke and the Thruſh, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Woodcocke be combroſe to kil: and therfore when you come to a Groue of Trées, or Thicket of Buſhes, caſt your Sparhawke into the trée and beate the buſhes, and at the riſing of the Fowle ſhe will be ſure to haue her. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, if that there were a ſhip fraught full of Hawkes, if there were but one Sparhawke amongſt them, there ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:11193:20"/> be no Cuſtome paid for any of them, and therefore ſhe is in diuers reſpects, a Sparhawke.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>How a Hawke flyeth.</head>
                     <p>AN Hawke flyeth to the riuer diuers waies, and ſhe ſlayeth the fowle diuerſly, that is to ſay, to the vew, or to the beake, or the toll: and all is but one, as ye ſhall vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand hereafter. She ſlayeth alſo to the querre, to the créepe, and no more waies but thoſe thrée, and ſhe nimmeth fowle at the ferre Iute, or at the Iuttie ferre.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Now ye ſhall know the meaning of theſe tearmes, Randon, Creepe, Emewed.</head>
                     <p>YOur Goſhawke or Tercell that ſhall flye to the vew, to the toll, or to the beake: in this manner ſhe muſt be taught. You muſt finde a Fowle in the Riuer, or in the Pit, and ſet your Hawke a good ſpace from you vpon a Molehill, or vpon the ground, and créepe ſoftly to the fowle, and when you come néere where the fowle lieth, looke backe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to the Hawke, and with your hand becke your Hawke to come to you, and when ſhe is on wing, and commeth low by the ground, and is almoſt at you, then ſmite your Hawke pole and crie hue, hue, hue, and make the fowle riſe, and then the Hawke will nime her.</p>
                     <p>And now, if your Hawke nime the Fowle on the farre ſide of the riuer, or the pit, from you, then ſhe ſlaies the Fowle at the ferre Iute, and if ſhe ſlay it vpon that ſide ye be on, as it may hap diuers times, then you ſhall ſay ſhe hath ſlaine the Fowle at the Iuttye ferre. If your Hawke ſlay the Fowle aloft, ye ſhall ſay ſhe tooke it at the mount, or at the foure.</p>
                     <p>And if the Fowle riſe not but flye along after the Riuer, and the Hawke nime her, then ye ſhall ſay ſhe ſlew it at ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don. And if your Hawke flieth at or to the Créep, when you haue your Hawke on your fiſt, and that you créepe ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Riuer or to the Pit, and ſtealeth to the brinke
<pb facs="tcp:11193:21"/> thereof, and then cry hue, and then by that meane nime the Fowle, then is ſhe ſlayne at the Créepe, at the ferre Iutte, or Iuttie ferre: and if it happen, as it doth often, that the Fowle for feare of your Hawke will riſe and fall into the riuer againe, or ere the Hawke ſée her, and ſo lye ſtill and dare not ariſe, then you ſhall ſay your Hawke hath enued the Fowle into the Riuer, and there be more Fowles in the Riuer then your Hawke pimmeth, and they dare not ariſe for feare of your Hawke.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>A Theffe.</head>
                     <p>YOu ſhall vnderſtand that your Goſhawke muſt not flye to the Riuer with belles in no wiſe: and therefore a Goſhawke is called a Theffe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Querre.</head>
                     <p>YOur Hawke flyeth to the Querre, when there be in the ſtumble time, Sardes of Mallards in the field, and when ſhe eſpieth them and commeth couert her ſelfe, and flye pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uely to the hedges or low by the ground, and nime one of them are they riſe, then you may ſay that the Fowle was flame at the Querre. But the generall vſe in theſe dayes of the word Querre, is when you firſt enter your Hawke: the firſt Fowle ſhée ſlayeth, is ſlaine at the Querre: and the Hawke that ſo ſlayeth, is ſaide to be Querried, as much as to ſay, the firſt ſéeking out, or finding of the Fowle.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Marke this tearme, Draw.</head>
                     <p>SOme miſuſe this tearme Draw, and ſay that their Hawke will draw to the Riuer: and that tearme draw, is properly aſſigned to that Hawke that will ſlay a Rooke, or a Crow, or a Rauen vpon the land ſitting: and then it may be ſaid that ſuch an Hawke doth draw well to a Rooke.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb facs="tcp:11193:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <head>If you will make your Hawke to the Querre, you muſt vſe her in this manner.</head>
                     <p>TAke a tame Mallard and ſet him in a plaine field, and let him goe where he will, then ſet your Hawke vpon your ſiſt, and go to that plaine, and hold vp your hand a prety way off from the Mallard, and looke if your Hawke can eſpie it by her owne courage: and if ſhe haue found the Fowle and deſire to flye to it, let her kill it, and plume well vpon it, and ſerue her ſo thrée or foure times, and then ſhe is made to the Querre.</p>
                     <p>I haue knowne Gentlemen that when they haue ſéene any tame Ducks, that if their Hawkes haue deſired to flye at them, they haue let them flye, to the encouraging of them another time, and ſo haue woone them to the Querre.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>A pretie deuice to take a Hawke that is broken out of Mew, and all manner of other Fowles that ſit in trees, or that hath taken vp their perch all night in any place.</head>
                     <p>YOu muſt in the night doe it. Climbe vp ſoftly, with a Skonce or a Lanterne, and you muſt haue but one light in your hand, and let the light be towards the Hawke or Fowle, that ſhe ſée not your face, and you may take her by the legs or any other place of her as you liſt. This is approued: for I haue knowne diuers that haue taken ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Fowles after this ſame manner.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the Bels of the Hawkes.</head>
                     <p>LOoke that the Bels that your Hawke ſhall weare that they be not too heauie, nor that they be aboue her power to beare, and that they be not one heauier then another, but that they be both of a waight: alſo looke that they haue a good ſound and ſhrill, and not both of one ſound, but that one be of a ſéemy time aboue the other, and that they be whole and not broken, eſpecially in the ſounding place: for if they be any whit broken, they will ſound fully.</p>
                     <p>Of Sparhawkes belles there is diuers choyce, and little
<pb facs="tcp:11193:22"/> charge of them, for there is plenty of them: and for Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hawkes, the bels of Millame were counted the beſt, and they are very good: for commonly they are founded with Siluer, and therefore they are ſold thereafter. There are now vſed of Dutchland bels, made in a towne called Dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dright, and they are excellent good bels, for they are well ſorted, and well ſounded, very good in ringing, of Shrilneſſe, and paſſing well laſting.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>How to reforme Hawkes that will carry away their Pray.</head>
                     <p>DIuers Hawkes, partly by being ſcarred by the indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>créete raſhneſſe of vnſkilfull Faulconers, and partly by being accuſtomed to pray vpon ſmall birds, will when they haue ſlaine any thing, carry it away vp into trées or other places, where gorging themſelues they will neglect their due obedience to their feeder, which to preuent you ſhall not at any time let your Hawke féede vpon quicke Birds, vnleſſe the creance be fixed thereunto, ſo that when ſhe would carry ſhe muſt looſe her pray, this will ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>cke her, and make her forbeare: Beſides you ſhall not at any time caſt her forth any foode, Pigeon, or other, but you ſhall firſt tie it faſt to a heauy lure, ſuch as ſhe cannot raiſe from the ground, and if notwithſtanding ſhe be ſtill apt to that euill, you ſhall then make a big round button of leather, and fire it vnder the ball of her foote, in ſuch ſort that ſhe cannot by any meanes truſſe any thing, and thus you may at your pleaſure flie her without any feare of carrying.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Here endeth the Booke of Hawking, and hereafter inſueth the names of all manner of Hawkes, and to whom they belong.</head>
                     <p>THeſe Hawkes belong to an Emperour, and theſe be their names: an Egle, a Bautere, a Melion: the ſimpleſt of theſe thrée wil ſlay a Calfe, a Fawne, a Roe, a Kid, a Trane, a Buſtard, a Storke, a Swanne, or a Foxe on the
<pb facs="tcp:11193:22"/> plaine ground: and theſe are not in lure, nor reclaimed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they be ſo ponderous to the Perch portatif: and theſe thrée by their nature belongs to an Emperour.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Theſe Hawkes belong to a King.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A</hi> Gerfaulcon, a Tercell of a Gerfaulcon, are due to a King.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>For a Prince.</head>
                     <p>THere is a Faulcon gentle, and a Tercel gentle, and theſe be for a Prince.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>For a Duke.</head>
                     <p>THere is a Faulcon of the Rocke, and that is for a Duke.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>For an Earle.</head>
                     <p>THere is a Faulcon Perigrine, and that is for an Earle.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>For a Baron.</head>
                     <p>THere is a Baſterd, and that is for a Baron.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Hawkes for a Knight.</head>
                     <p>THere is a Sacre and a Sacret, and thoſe be for a Knight.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Hawkes for a Squier.</head>
                     <p>THere is a Lauer, and a Laueret, &amp; thoſe be for a Squier.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>For a Lady.</head>
                     <p>THere is a Merlion, and that Hawke is for a Ladie.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>An Hawke for a young man.</head>
                     <p>THere is a Hobbie, and that is for a young man.</p>
                     <p>And theſe be Hawkes of the Tower, and be both il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lured, and be called and reclaymed.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div n="2 (hunting)" type="book">
                  <pb facs="tcp:11193:23"/>
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The Booke of Hunting: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto <hi>is added the meaſures of Blowing,</hi> very pleaſant to be read, for all thoſe that haue delight in the Art of Venerie.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S in the Booke of Hawking is diſcourſed and noted the proper tearmes belonging to that Gentleman like exerciſe: So in like manner is ſhewed in this Treatiſe of Hunting, for all ſorts of beaſtes of Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerie, and alſo is ſhewed all conuenient tearmes, as well of Hounds as of Beaſts, or any other that appertaine to the Art of Venerie.</p>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of Beaſtes of Venery there be foure ſorts.</head>
                     <p>THe Hart, the Bore, the Wolfe, and the Hare.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Beaſtes of Chaſe there be fiue kindes.</head>
                     <p>THe Bucke, the Roe, the Martyron, the Foxe and the Doe: and theſe are the fiue beaſts of Chaſe, and if you chance to finde any other, you ſhall call them Raſcall.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the Age of an Hart.</head>
                     <p>THe firſt yéere he is a Calfe, the ſecond yéere a Broket, the third yéere a Spayd, the fourth yéere a Stagge, and the fift yéere a great Stagge, and at the ſixt yéere he is an Hart.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>To know the head of an Hart.</head>
                     <p>YOu ſhall call the head of a Hart, Anteler, Riall, and Surriall, and when you may know him by the top, you
<pb facs="tcp:11193:23"/> ſhall call him forked a Hart of tenne, and when he beareth thrée in the top, you ſhall call him a Hart of twelue, and when he beareth foure you ſhall call him ſummed, a Hart of ſixtéene, and from foure forward you ſhall call him ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of ſo many as he carieth, how many ſo euer they be.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of a Heard, a Beuie, a Sounder, or a Rout.</head>
                     <p>OF Hart, Hinde, Bucke, and Doe, you ſhall euer ſay a heard, of Roes you ſhall euer tearme a Beuie, of wilde Swine a Sounder, and of Wolues a rout.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of Heards, and their ſeuerall kindes.</head>
                     <p>EYther of red Deare, which onely are Harts or Hindes, or fallow Deare, which are Bucke and Doe, you ſhall call vpon the view, twentie, a little heard, fortie a middle heard, and eightie a great heard. Now you ſhall vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that a Bucke is the firſt yéere a Fawne, the ſecond a Pricket, the third a Sorrell, the fourth a Sore, at what time he will ſerue for a warrant, and the fift a Bucke of the firſt head.</p>
                     <p>Vpon the view of a Hart, if he be a goodly Deare, you ſhall not call him fayre, but a great Hart, or a great Hinde, or a great Bucke: But a Doe you ſhall call a fayre Doe, theſe are the true tearmes of a perfect wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of Roes.</head>
                     <p>SIxe Roes or vnder is a ſmall Beuie, fenne is a middle Beuie, twelue is a great Beuie, and ſtill the greater the number, the greater is the Beuie.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of wilde Swine.</head>
                     <p>TWelue is a ſmall founder of wilde Swine, ſixtéene a middle ſounder, and twentie a great ſounder.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb facs="tcp:11193:24"/>
                     <head>Of Hunting the Roe, and the rights thereunto.</head>
                     <p>VVHen you ſhall Hunt the Roe, you ſhall ſay, hée croſſes, and trauerſſes before the Hounds, or if you ſay he doubles, it is not much amiſſe, although by the lawes of <hi>Sir Triſtram,</hi> it is hardly permitted. You ſhall not ſay, this is a great Roe-bucke, but a faire Bucke, and a faire Doe. Dreſſing or breaking vp of a Roe, is called the Herdling of a Roe, which you ſhall performe in this ſort, you ſhall lay the head betwéene the two forelegs, then take the two hinder legs, and croſſing them, put them, ore the two contrary fore legs, faſtning them by the looſening of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ioynts, onely taking out the bowells and the blood, and cutting off the féete, wherewith you ſhall reward your Hounds, diuiding each foote into foure péeces with your wood-knife, and putting them amongſt the bowels and blood, giue it the Hounds, for this is their reward onely.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the Bore, and his rights.</head>
                     <p>TO ſpeake firſt, of the age of the wild Bore, he is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the firſt yéere a Pigge of the Sounder, the ſecond yéere he is a Hogge, the third yéere, a Hog-ſtere, the fourth, a Bore, for then (if not before) he departeth from the Sounder, and then he is called a ſingler. Now, when you haue ſlaine the Bore, you ſhall vndoe him, firſt: taking off the ſkinne, and in dreſſing him orderly diuide the fleſh into two and thirtie bredthes, as it is termed amongſt wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. If he be ſlaine by the ſtrength of the Hounds, you ſhall giue them the bowells vpon the ground in the ſame place where he was killed, which alſo is called a reward.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the Hare, and her rights.</head>
                     <p>THe Hare is the King of all the beaſts of venerie, and in Hunting maketh the beſt ſport, bréedeth the moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light of any other, and is a beaſt moſt ſtrange by nature, for he often changeth his kinde, and is both male and female:
<pb facs="tcp:11193:24"/> and this is a ſtrange thing in the female, and onely peculiar to this beaſt of all other: after ſhe hath taken the Bucke, and commeth to kindle, ſhe bringeth forth two Leuerits, rough, and in perfect ſhape, and retaineth two other in her ſtill, which ſhe bringeth forth before the two firſt be well a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to reléeue, and ſhe is knotted for her third Leuerit, and all this at one time. We tearme the place where ſhe fitteth, her Forme, the place through which ſhe goeth to releefe, her Muſet, and when we find where ſhe hath gone, we call it the pricking out of the Hare, except it be in the Snow, and then we call it the trayning out of the Hare: her deceits, and ſhifts, before the Hounds, we call her doubling, and her fée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, we call her reléefe. The Hare beareth ſewet, &amp; greaſe, ſhe fimaſheth, crottiſes, and ranges, although amongſt the Huntſmen of theſe latter times, theſe tearmes be worne out of vſe, onely we ſay ſhe crottiſſes. When the Hare is gone to her Forme, we ſay euer ſhe is gone to her ſeate, and we ſay the Hare ſitteth, whereas, ſpeaking of other beaſts, we ſay they lie, &amp; the reaſon is, becauſe ſhe euer buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vpon her leggs, as though Nature had taught her to haue her féete euer in readineſſe, being of all other beaſts the moſt watchfull: and ſhe naturally deſireth to runne vp the hill, becauſe her leggs be ſhorter before then behind, and the ſewet, or greaſe, which ſhe beareth, lieth ouer the loynes, betwéene the chine and the taile, yet we doe not ſay the Hare is fat, but the Hare is white.</p>
                     <p>Now if you goe about to Hunt this nimble and delicate chace, you ſhall when you come to the kennell (in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning) to couple vp your Hounds, firſt gibell once, or twice, to awake &amp; ſtir vp the dogs, then opening the kennell dore, the Huntſman ſhall vſe ſome gentill words of ratling, leaſt in their haſt comming out, they ſhould hurt one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, to which the Frenchman vſeth this word <hi>Arere, Arere,</hi> or as we ſay in Engliſh, ſoft, ſoft, ho, ho, ho, ho, once or twice redoubling the ſame, coupling them as they come out of the kennell: and being come into the field, and hauing
<pb facs="tcp:11193:25"/> vncoupled, the Frenchman vſeth to ſay, <hi>Hors de coople auaunt, auaunt,</hi> once or twice, with <hi>So-how</hi> thrée times together. We vſe to gibet once or twice to the doggs, cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>a trayle, a trayle, there doggs there:</hi> and if it be in a Buſhie place, to beate the Buſhes with your Hunting-Pole, and crie, <hi>Hup wat, hup,</hi> which makes the doggs in trailing to hold cloſe together, crying often <hi>So-how.</hi> And if the Hounds haue had reſt, and being ouer-luſtie, doe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to fling about, the Frenchmen vſe to cry, <hi>Sweft a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, Sweft,</hi> redoubling the ſame, or elſe, <hi>Arere amies, ho ho,</hi> and we in Engliſh vſe to the ſame purpoſe, <hi>Soft ho, ho, here againe ho, ho,</hi> doubling the ſame: ſometimes cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them backe againe, with a gibet or hallow, pointing with your Hunting-pole vpon the ground, and crying <hi>So-how.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Now, if ſome one of the Hounds, light vpon a pure ſent, ſo that by the manner of his eager ſpending, you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it is very good, you ſhall cry <hi>There, now there, or thats it, thats it,</hi> and to put the reſt of the cry into him, you ſhall cry <hi>Auaunt auaunt, ho, liſt a Talbot, liſt there, liſt,</hi> to which the Frenchman vſeth <hi>Oles, a Talbot, le Vailant oies, oies troue le coward,</hi> in the ſame manner with little difference: and if you finde by your Hounds where a Hare hath béene at reliefe, if it be in the time of gréene Corne, and if your Hounds ſpend vpon the traile merily, and make a good cry, then ſhall the Huntſman wind thrée motes with his Horne, which he may ſundry times vſe with diſcretion, when he ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Hounds haue made away, a double, and make on towards the ſeate. Now, if it be within ſome field or pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, where the Hare hath béene at reliefe, let the Huntſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man caſt a ring with his Hounds to finde where ſhe hath gone out, which if the Hounds light vpon, he ſhall cry, <hi>There boyes there, that, tat, tat, hoe, heck auaunt, liſt to him liſt,</hi> and if they chance by their brameſickneſſe to ouer ſhoote it, he ſhall call to his Hounds, <hi>ho, againe ho,</hi> doubling the ſame twice, and if vndertaking it againe and making it
<pb facs="tcp:11193:25"/> good, he ſhall then cheare his hounds and ſay, <hi>There to him, there, that's it, that tat tat,</hi> blowing a Mote. And note that this word <hi>ſo how,</hi> is generally vſed at the view of any beaſt of Chaſe or Venery, but indéed the word is properly, <hi>ſa ho,</hi> and not <hi>ſo how,</hi> but for the better pronunciation and fulneſſe of the ſame, we ſay <hi>ſo how,</hi> not <hi>ſa ho.</hi> Now the hounds running in full Chaſe, the French-men vſe to ſay <hi>ho ho,</hi> or <hi>Swef, alieu, doute alieu,</hi> and we imitating them, ſay, <hi>there boys, there, auant there, to him there,</hi> which tearmes are indéed deriued from their language. Now we finde the old &amp; ancient huntſmen had diuers tearmes vpon the view of the pricking of the Hare, which although I finde not very néedfull yet for the Loue I beare vnto antiquity, I will not omit, as when the Hare hath gone ouer ſome graſſie place where her pricks cannot be ſéene but onely by ſtayning the graſſe, or by breaking ſome looſe mould, we ſay ſhe <hi>ſorths</hi> or <hi>reſorths,</hi> but theſe tearmes I will leaue to the indifferent opinion of the ſkilfull huntſman.</p>
                     <p>Now the reaſon why they ſay the Hare fumaces and <hi>crots</hi> or <hi>crottiſes</hi> is this, we ſay the Hare fumayes, becauſe ſhe beareth ſewet, and ſhe crottiſeth becauſe ſhe beareth greaſe, and becauſe ſhe croucheth on the houghs when ſhe letteth it goe: So that we ſay all beaſts which beare tallow, &amp; ſtand vpright fumayne as they go, all that crouch or ſtoope do not.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The Hounds reward from the Hare.</head>
                     <p>WHen your hounds by fierce &amp; good hunting haue kild the Hare, you ſhall reward them with the ſhoulders and the ſides, with the head and all the intrails, excepting on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the gall (for it is precious and medicinal) which reward be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing delt them is called the <hi>Hallow</hi> of all good huntſmen. But the hinder loynes being excellent meate, and if the dreſſing be anſwerable, as daintie veniſon as any can be, it ſhall be neceſſary to preſerue them, and beare them home for your owne reward. Now there is another beaſt which goeth to reléefe as well as the Hare, which is a thing of eſpeciall good
<pb facs="tcp:11193:26"/> note amongſt all good huntſmen, and that is the Stag, who from the Annunciation of our Lady, till Saint <hi>Peters</hi> day, is euer ſaid to goe to reléefe as well as the Hare.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of flaying and ſtripping of Beaſtes.</head>
                     <p>WHen beaſts are ſlaine, which ſhall be flayed, and which ſtript, according to their natures and kinds: know that all which beare ſewet, and raunge, according to the old En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh tearmes, ſhall be ſaid to be flayed, the Hare onely excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, which ſhall be ſaid onely to be ſtripped, or caſed, and ſo of the Otter or Badger, and generally ſo all beaſts that goe to reléefe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>More of the Roe, and his rights.</head>
                     <p>THe <hi>Roebuck</hi> is the firſt yéere a Kid, ſucking on his Dam, the ſecond yéere he is called a <hi>Gerle,</hi> the third yéere a <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male,</hi> the fourth yéere a <hi>Roe-bucke</hi> of the firſt head, the fift yéere a <hi>Roe-bucke:</hi> he vſeth to caſt his hornes at S. <hi>Andrews</hi> tide, &amp; his nature is to hide them in ſome Moore, or in ſome Marſh ground, ſo that they are very ſeldome found, at Saint <hi>Iames</hi> tide he euer goeth to the <hi>Roe,</hi> which when he doth, we ſay he goeth in his turne. Now if you kill a <hi>Roe-buck</hi> which is high in greaſe, you ſhall dreſſe the veniſon of it as of a <hi>Hart</hi> or a <hi>Hinde:</hi> we vſe to ſay in rutting time that a Stag Bellowes, a Bucke groynes, and a <hi>Roe-bucke</hi> Kels, which they vſe in the time of their rut, and we vſe to ſay the Foxe and the Wolfe doe barke and houle.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The ſeaſon of all ſorts of Venerie.</head>
                     <p>THe time of greaſe beginneth at <hi>Midſommer</hi> day, and continueth till <hi>Holy-rood</hi> day, and then is the Stag, Bucke, and Sore in ſeaſon.</p>
                     <p>The ſeaſon of the <hi>Roe-buck</hi> is from Eaſter til <hi>Michaelmas.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The ſeaſon of the Foxe is from the Natiuitie till the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciation of our Ladie.</p>
                     <p>The ſeaſon of the Doe or Roe, is from <hi>Michaelmas</hi> till <hi>Candlemas.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The ſeaſon of the Hare is from <hi>Michaelmas</hi> til <hi>Midſomer.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11193:26"/>
                     <p>The ſeaſon of the Wolfe is as the ſeaſon of the Foxe.</p>
                     <p>The ſeaſon of the Bore is from the Natiuitie till the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rification of our Ladie.</p>
                     <p>Now in the hunting of the Hart or Stag, being of all the moſt princely &amp; royall chaſe, it giueth an excéeding grace vnto a huntſman to vſe the tearmes fit and proper vnto the ſame, which I wil here ſet down as receiued from antiquity.</p>
                     <p>Firſt when we ſée where the Hart hath gone, we vſe to ſay, here he breaketh, or here appeareth his ſlott, and when the Hart entreth a Riuer or Poole (which we call the ſoyle) we ſay he deſcendeth, and when we find where he lept into the Riuer, we ſay he profereth, becauſe we are vncertaine whether he goeth out at ſome other place, or returneth the ſame way againe. And if he turne the ſame way againe, we ſay he <hi>Reprofereth</hi> &amp; when we find where he hath come out of the other ſide of the riuer we call it the ſoyle, and being come out of the water, which filles his footſteps, we call it defoulling.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>How you ſhall vndoe, or breake-vp a Hart.</head>
                     <p>AFter the fall of the Hart or Stag, and that the huntſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are come in together, and haue winded the death of the Hart, you ſhal lay him vpright vpon his hornes which is called ſuing of the Hart, then let the beſt man in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, or ſome perſonage of account take the aſſay before the aſſembly, which done, then firſt cut off the cods, then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin at the Iawes, and ſlit him downe to the aſſay, and ſo directly downe to the cods: which being done, begin firſt to ſlit the left leg before, and next the left leg behinde, which you muſt not forget in any hand before you goe to the right ſide, which you muſt performe next in the ſame manner: the which being done, begin at the chéeke on the left ſide, from which directly take off the ſkinne downe to the breaſt, and ſo downe to the aſſay, and to the place of the end: then begin at the other ſide, and doe the ſame in like manner, but cut not the tayle of the beaſt (which we call the ſingle) away in any hand, but cutting off the ſkin let it remayne to the hanches,
<pb facs="tcp:11193:27"/> then ſpreading the ſkin abroad, let the bodie be laid vpon the ſame, very open, and begin firſt to make the Arbor, which is the conduit which leadeth vnto the ſtomacke, guts and bag, and muſt be made faſt and cloſe by a round knot, then cut out the ſhoulders, which muſt be done with a very long broad poynted knife, wherein you muſt obſerue to kéepe the outſide of the inner ſkin whole, and lay it cloſe to the ſide: then open the belly, and take out the ſewet: which is moſt excellent and needfull for Surgions, then putting in your hand vnder the breaſt bone, pul downe the Arbor, &amp; turning out the panch, take away the rate, filling it with the bloud &amp; ſewet, hauing a néedle, and a thread ready to ſow it vp with: then ſearching into the ſmall guts, take out the maw, and next the liuer, lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them vpon the ſkin, next after theſe take out the bladder, then going to the vmbles, firſt looſen the aduancers which do leane to the necke, and taking the throat or weſſand, looſen the fillets very circumſpectly, which fals to the vmbles, and muſt be gathered and ſtripped vpon the weſſand with the ſame, with the naues &amp; ſewet, and the fleſh along the midriff from both the ſides, and ſo like a huntſman make vp the vm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles with all theſe together, only kéepe the lights vpon the ſkin: This being done, ſlit the ſkin wherin the Hart is infol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, &amp; take away the haires which grow about the ſame, and in caruing the Hart you ſhal find a bone therein, which hath the vertue to cure the malady called the paſſion of the heart, then cutting away the looſe ſkirts, fil them with bloud to ſaue the melting of the greaſe: then cut away the necke from both the ſides, &amp; take the head away from the neck, taking out the tongue &amp; the braine, laying them with the lights, the ſmall guts, and the bloud vpon the ſkinne, to reward the hounds, which is called the Querrie. The left ſhoulder of the Hart is, his fée which dreſſeth him, and ſo is the ſkin and the right ſhoulder the Forreſters fée.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The names of the ſeuerall parts which make vp the vmbles of a Deare.</head>
                     <p>THat part of the vmbles which cleaue vnto the throat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bole is called the aduancers, and the hindermoſt part of
<pb facs="tcp:11193:27"/> the vmbles be called the Forchers, the other are called the crookes of the vmbles: Now in the Hart the chiefe part and ſubſtance is called the Gargilon, and the other parts are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the crookes and rundell.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The vndoing or dreſſing of the wild Bore.</head>
                     <p>AS hath béene before ſaid, you ſhall make two and thirty breadths of a wilde Bore. The firſt is the head, the next to that is the coller, which is the beſt of the Swine, then two ſhields, and the two ſhoulders, and diuide each ſide of the ſwine into thrée parts, the peſtell and the gam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bones, accounting a two, then the two fillets, the legs &amp; the féet diuided into eight parts, diuiding the chine into foure ſundry péeces, then put the greaſe of the Bore into his blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and preſerue the ſame as a thing paſſing medicinable.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the Vantlay, the Lay, and Relay, with Forloyning, and ſuch like tearmes.</head>
                     <p>THis is properly called a Vauntlay in hunting, when the hounds are in the chaſe of a Hart, and that you ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doubt their ſpéed, or finde them farre caſt behinde, you doe vncouple freſh hounds, and hallowing them in to the Déere, force him to more ſpéed then before, which may be a meanes to caſt off the other hounds which be behinde. Now a Lay is this, when the Hart is in full chaſe, you lying néere to ſome couert, doe there ſhake off ſome freſh hounds in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the crie, to ſupply and make it the ſtronger, if ſome ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haled Dogs ſhould happen to ſinke in the latter end of the chaſe. A Relay, is when you ſhal vncouple ſome freſh hounds and cheare them, when as the reſt of the Dogs be alreadie gone away with the Hart, and almoſt out of the hearing of the crie, and this is called a Relay: Now for forloyning, it is, when you finde any chaſe within ſome couert, and ſome mute or light running hounds fall in with the ſame, being ſtolne out of the couert: this is of huntſmen called For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyning, for they driue the chaſe ſo faſt on before, that the huntſmen cannot lay the reſt of the crie in with the ſame.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb facs="tcp:11193:28"/>
                     <head>Of the Hornes of a Bucke.</head>
                     <p>THée Hornes of euery fallow Déere muſt bée ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med: or euer hée be a Bucke hée muſt haue two pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Branches, and foure and twentie Eſpelers, which when he hath, you may very well tearme him a very great Bucke: and this we ſée in common experience, that oft in Hunting of the Hare, or the Bucke: the Hounds to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the fall of the chaſe, hold together, and come ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the reaſon being thréefold which maketh them continue, and incourageth them much: the firſt is, that when the Hart, or Bucke, beginneth to be imboſted, he caſteth out of his mouth a froth, which is wonderfull ſwéete to the Hounds, which he leaueth vpon the hearbs and Buſhes: the ſecond is, when he ſweateth, the ſweate runneth downe from his body to his cleys, which the Hounds finding, know well he ſincketh: the third is, that by reaſon of his wearineſſe, and toyle, the ſewet is very ſtrong, and hot, and eaſily entereth the noſes of the doggs, which meruay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly encourageth them to his death.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Beaſts of the Chaſe of ſweete foote and of ſtincking.</head>
                     <p>ANd thoſe are the Bucke, the Doe, the Beare, the Rayndéere, the Eylke, the Spikerd, the Ottor, and the Martron.</p>
                     <p>There be beaſtes of the Chaſe, of the ſtincking foote: the Roe-bucke, and the Roe, the Fulmard, the Iches, the Baude, the Gray, the Foxe, the Squirrell, the white Rat, the Sotte, and the Polcat.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The names of diuers Hounds.</head>
                     <p>FIrſt there is a Greyhound, a Hound, and a Spanyel, a Baſtard, a Mungrell, a Maſtiffe, a Lemor, Raches, Ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, Terrours, Butchers Hounds, Dunghill doggs, Trindle tailes, and prick-eared Curres, and ſmall Ladie
<pb facs="tcp:11193:28"/> Puppies, that beare away the fleas and diuers ſmall faults.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The properties of a good Greyhound.</head>
                     <p>HEaded like a Snake, necked like a Drake, footed like a Cat, tayled like a Rat, ſided like a Breame, and backt like a Beame: The firſt yéere he learneth to féede, the ſecond yéere to field him leade, the third he is fellow like, the fourth yéere none ſike, the fift yéere good enough, the ſixt yéere he ſhall hold the Plough, the ſeauenth yéere he will auaile great Bitches to aſſaile, the eight yéere licke ladle, the ninth yéere cart ſaddle: and when he is come to that yéere, haue him to the Tanner:</p>
                     <p>For the beſt Greyhound that euer you had,</p>
                     <p>At the ninth yéere he is full bad.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The proper tearmes and names of companies of Beaſtes and Fowles, with others.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>AN heard of Hares.</item>
                        <item>An heard of all manner of Déere.</item>
                        <item>An heard of Swannes.</item>
                        <item>An heard of Craines.</item>
                        <item>An heard of Curlewes.</item>
                        <item>An heard of Wrenes.</item>
                        <item>An heard of Harlots.</item>
                        <item>Any of Feſants.</item>
                        <item>A Beuie of Ladies.</item>
                        <item>A cete of Greyes.</item>
                        <item>A Berry of Conies.</item>
                        <item>A Riches of Matrons.</item>
                        <item>A Beſenes of Firets.</item>
                        <item>A brace of Greyhounds .ij.</item>
                        <item>A leaſe of Greyhounds .iij.</item>
                        <item>A couple of Spaniels.</item>
                        <item>A couple of running Hounds.</item>
                        <item>A litter of Whelps.</item>
                        <item>A Kindle of young Cats.</item>
                        <item>A Beuy of Roes.</item>
                        <item>A Beuy of Quailes.</item>
                        <item>A ſiege of Herons.</item>
                        <item>A ſiege of Bytours.</item>
                        <item>A ſore or a ſuce of Mallards.</item>
                        <item>A muſter of Peacockes.</item>
                        <item>A walke of Snites.</item>
                        <item>A congregation of people.</item>
                        <item>An exalting of Larkes.</item>
                        <item>A watch of Nightingales.</item>
                        <item>An hoſt of men.</item>
                        <item>A fellowſhip of Yeomen.</item>
                        <item>A cherme of Goldfinches.</item>
                        <item>A caſt of bread.</item>
                        <item>A couple or payre of Bottles.</item>
                        <item>A flight of Doues.</item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:11193:29"/>
                        <item>An vnkindnes of Rauens.</item>
                        <item>A clattering of Choughes.</item>
                        <item>A diſſimulation of Birds.</item>
                        <item>A route of Knights.</item>
                        <item>A pride of Lyons.</item>
                        <item>A ſlouth of Beares.</item>
                        <item>A draught of Butlers.</item>
                        <item>A proud ſhewing of Taylors.</item>
                        <item>A temperance of Cookes.</item>
                        <item>A ſtalke of Foſters.</item>
                        <item>A hoſte of Souldiours.</item>
                        <item>A laughter of Oſtlers.</item>
                        <item>A gloſing of Tauerners.</item>
                        <item>A malepertnes of Pedlers.</item>
                        <item>A thraue of Threſſhers.</item>
                        <item>A ſquat of Dawbers.</item>
                        <item>A fighting of Beggers.</item>
                        <item>A ſinguler of Bores.</item>
                        <item>A drift of tame Swine.</item>
                        <item>A harraſe of Horſe.</item>
                        <item>A ragge of colthor or a rake.</item>
                        <item>A Baren of Mules.</item>
                        <item>A trip of Gotes.</item>
                        <item>A gaggle of Géeſe.</item>
                        <item>A broode of Hens.</item>
                        <item>A badling of Duckes.</item>
                        <item>A nonpatients of wiues.</item>
                        <item>A ſtate of Princes.</item>
                        <item>A thought of Barons.</item>
                        <item>A prudence of Vicaries.</item>
                        <item>A ſuperfluitie of Nunnes.</item>
                        <item>A ſchoole of Clarkes.</item>
                        <item>A doctrine of Doctors.</item>
                        <item>A conuerting of Preachers.</item>
                        <item>A ſentence of Iudges.</item>
                        <item>A damning of Iurours.</item>
                        <item>An obeiſance of ſeruants.</item>
                        <item>A ſeate of Vſhers.</item>
                        <item>A tygenes of Pyes.</item>
                        <item>A hoſt of Sparrowes.</item>
                        <item>A ſwarme of Bées.</item>
                        <item>A caſt of Hawkes of the To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, two.</item>
                        <item>A leaſe of the ſame Hawkes.</item>
                        <item>A flight of Goſhawkes.</item>
                        <item>A flight of Swallowes.</item>
                        <item>A bilding of Rookes.</item>
                        <item>A murmuration of Stares.</item>
                        <item>A route of Wolues.</item>
                        <item>An vntruth of Sumners.</item>
                        <item>A melodie of Harpers.</item>
                        <item>A pouertie of Pipers.</item>
                        <item>A ſubtiltie of Serieants.</item>
                        <item>A tabernacle of Bakers.</item>
                        <item>A drift of Fiſhers.</item>
                        <item>A diſguiſing of Taylers.</item>
                        <item>A bleach of Souters.</item>
                        <item>A ſmere of Curriours.</item>
                        <item>A cluſter of Grapes.</item>
                        <item>A Cluſter of Churles.</item>
                        <item>A ragge of Maydens.</item>
                        <item>A raufull of Knaues.</item>
                        <item>A bluſh of Boyes.</item>
                        <item>An vncredibilitie of Cokolds.</item>
                        <item>A couie of Partriches.</item>
                        <item>A ſpring of Teles.</item>
                        <item>A deſart of Lapwings.</item>
                        <item>A fall of Woodcockes.</item>
                        <item>A congregation of Plouers.</item>
                        <item>A couert of Cotes.</item>
                        <item>A dule of Turtles.</item>
                        <item>A ſcull of Friers.</item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:11193:29"/>
                        <item>Abhominable ſight of Monks</item>
                        <item>A ſcale of Fiſh.</item>
                        <item>An example of Marters.</item>
                        <item>An obſeruance of Hermites.</item>
                        <item>An eloquence of Lawyers.</item>
                        <item>A faith of Marchants.</item>
                        <item>A prouiſion of Stewardes of houſes.</item>
                        <item>A kerfe of Panters.</item>
                        <item>A credence of Sewers.</item>
                        <item>A leap of Lybards.</item>
                        <item>A ſhrewdnes of Apes.</item>
                        <item>A ſculke of Foxes.</item>
                        <item>A neſt of Rabites.</item>
                        <item>A labor of Moles.</item>
                        <item>A mute of Hounds.</item>
                        <item>A kenell of Raches.</item>
                        <item>A ſute of Lyam.</item>
                        <item>A cowardnes of Curres.</item>
                        <item>A ſourd of wild Swine.</item>
                        <item>A ſtod of Mares.</item>
                        <item>A pace of Aſſes.</item>
                        <item>A droue of Nete.</item>
                        <item>A flocke of Shéepe.</item>
                        <item>A gaggle of women.</item>
                        <item>A péepe of Chickens.</item>
                        <item>A multiply of Huſbands.</item>
                        <item>A pontifica of Prelates.</item>
                        <item>A dignitie of Chanons.</item>
                        <item>A charge of Curates.</item>
                        <item>A diſcretion of Prieſtes.</item>
                        <item>A diſworſhip of Scots.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Here followeth the proper tearmes belonging to the brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vp or dreſsing of diuers kinds of Beaſts, and Fowles, and Fiſhes.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Déere broken.</item>
                        <item>A Gooſe reared.</item>
                        <item>An embruing of Caruers.</item>
                        <item>A ſafegard of Porters.</item>
                        <item>A blaſt of Hunters.</item>
                        <item>A threatning of Courteours.</item>
                        <item>A promiſe of Tapſters.</item>
                        <item>A lying of Pardoners.</item>
                        <item>A miſbeléeue of Painters.</item>
                        <item>A laſh of Carters.</item>
                        <item>A ſcolding of Gameſters.</item>
                        <item>A wondring of Tinckers.</item>
                        <item>A waywardneſſe of Hawards</item>
                        <item>A worſhip of Writers.</item>
                        <item>A neuer thriuing of Iuglers.</item>
                        <item>A fraunch of Myllers.</item>
                        <item>A feaſt of Brewars.</item>
                        <item>A goring of Butchers.</item>
                        <item>A trinket of Coruiſers.</item>
                        <item>A plucke of Shooturners.</item>
                        <item>A dronken ſhip of Coblers.</item>
                        <item>A cluſter of Nuttes.</item>
                        <item>A roge of teeth.</item>
                        <item>A raſcall of Boyes.</item>
                        <item>An Egge tyred.</item>
                        <item>A Frier trimbred.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of Fiſhes.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Salmon chined.</item>
                        <item>A Pike ſplated.</item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:11193:30"/>
                        <item>A Hadocke ſided.</item>
                        <item>A Cheuin finned.</item>
                        <item>A Sole loyned.</item>
                        <item>A Gurnard chined.</item>
                        <item>A Tench ſawſed.</item>
                        <item>An Ele trouchened.</item>
                        <item>A Breame ſplayd.</item>
                        <item>A Barble tuſked.</item>
                        <item>A Trout gobbetted.</item>
                        <item>A Pigge headed and ſided.</item>
                        <item>A Capon ſawſed.</item>
                        <item>A Cheuin fruſhed.</item>
                        <item>A Conie vnlaſed.</item>
                        <item>A Craine diſplayed.</item>
                        <item>A Curlew v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ioynted.</item>
                        <item>A Feſant alete.</item>
                        <item>A Quaile winged.</item>
                        <item>A Plouer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>uinſed.</item>
                        <item>A Pigion thied.</item>
                        <item>A Brawne leched.</item>
                        <item>A Swanne lift.</item>
                        <item>A Lambe ſhouldered.</item>
                        <item>A Kid ſhouldered.</item>
                        <item>A Hen ſpoyled.</item>
                        <item>A Mallard vnbraſed.</item>
                        <item>A Heron diſmembred.</item>
                        <item>A Peacocke diſfigured.</item>
                        <item>A Butter vntached.</item>
                        <item>A Partrich alet.</item>
                        <item>A Rayle breaſted.</item>
                        <item>A Woodcocke thied.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>You ſhall ſay thus.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Hart harboreth.</item>
                        <item>A Quire loggeth.</item>
                        <item>A Tyman beddeth.</item>
                        <item>Shouldring or leauing.</item>
                        <item>A Woodcock breaking.</item>
                        <item>A Bucke lodgeth.</item>
                        <item>A Roe bedeth.</item>
                        <item>An Hare in his forme.</item>
                        <item>A Conie ſitting.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The true and perfect meaſure of Blowing</head>
                     <p>FIrſt when you goe into the field, blow with one winde one ſhort, one long, and a longer.</p>
                     <p>To blow to the coupling of the Hounds at the Kennell doore, blow with one, one long and thrée ſhort.</p>
                     <p>The ſecond winde, one long, one ſhort, and a ſhorter.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>To blow to the field.</head>
                     <p>BLow with two windes: with the firſt one ſhort, one long, and two ſhort.</p>
                     <p>With the ſecond winde, one ſhort, one long, and a longer.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb facs="tcp:11193:30"/>
                     <head>To blow in the field.</head>
                     <p>VVIth two windes, the firſt two ſhort, one long and two ſhort.</p>
                     <p>The ſecond, one ſhort, one long and a longer.</p>
                     <p>To vncouple thy Hounds in the Field: thrée long notes, and with thrée windes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>To blow to ſeeke</head>
                     <p>TWo Windes: The firſt a long and a ſhort, the ſecond a long.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>When the Hounds hunt after a game vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne, blow thus.</head>
                     <p>BLow the Veline, one long, and ſixe ſhort: the ſecond winde, two ſhort and one long: the third winde, one long and two ſhort.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>To draw from Couert to Couert.</head>
                     <p>THrée windes, two ſhort, one long, and two ſhort. The ſecond, one long and a ſhort. The third, one long.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>To blow the earthing of the Foxe when he is couerable.</head>
                     <p>FOure notes with foure windes. The releife, one long, ſixe ſhort.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>To blow if the Foxe be not couerable.</head>
                     <p>TWo windes, one long and thrée ſhort. The ſecond winde long.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>To blow the death of the Foxe in field or couert.</head>
                     <p>THrée notes, with thrée windes, the rechate vpon the ſame with thrée windes.</p>
                     <p>THe firſt winde, one long and ſixe ſhort. The ſecond, one ſhort and one long. The third, one long and fiue ſhort.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The death of the Foxe at thy Lords gate.</head>
                     <p>TWo notes, and then the reliefe thrée times.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb facs="tcp:11193:31"/>
                     <head>The death of the Bucke, eyther with Bow or Hounds, or Grey-hounds.</head>
                     <p>ONe long Note.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The knowledge vpon the ſame.</head>
                     <p>TWo-ſhort and one long.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The death of the Bucke with Hounds.</head>
                     <p>TWo long notes, and the rechate.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The price of an Hart ryall.</head>
                     <p>NIne Notes with thrée reſtes. The Rechate with thrée winds. The firſt, one long and fiue ſhort. The ſecond, one long and one ſhort. The third, one long and ſixe ſhort.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>To blow the call of the keepers of any Parke or Forreſt.</head>
                     <p>ONe ſhort, one long, and a longer. If the kéeper an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere you, blow two ſhort with one winde, and draw towards him. And after that blow one ſhort.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>When the game breaketh couered.</head>
                     <p>FOure with thrée winds, and the Rechate vpon the ſame.</p>
                     <p>The ſtent when the hounds can hunt no further.</p>
                     <p>With thrée winds, the firſt, one long and ſixe ſhort. The ſecond, one long and one ſhort. The third, one long.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Where the Foxe is earthed blow for the Terriers after this manner.</head>
                     <p>ONe long and two ſhort. The ſecond winde one long and two ſhort.</p>
                     <p>Note this, for it is the chiefeſt and principalleſt point to be noted.</p>
                     <p>Euery long containeth in blowing ſeauen quauers, one Minome, and one quauer.</p>
                     <p>One Minome contayneth foure quauers.</p>
                     <p>One ſhort contayneth thrée quauers.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>The end of the meaſures of blowing.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:11193:31"/>
                  <p>A Briefe Treatiſe <hi>of Fowling.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Wherein is contained <hi>diuers proper Deuiſes</hi> both of Baytes and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: with the making of Bird-lime, the manner and order in vſing of it on your Lime-rods: with many other ſpeciall points, appertaining to that Exerciſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Iohn H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lme,</hi> and are to be ſould at his ſhop in Saint <hi>Dunſtanes</hi> Church-yard in Fleetſtreet. 1614.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="3 (fowling)" type="book">
                  <pb facs="tcp:11193:32"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11193:32"/>
                  <head>A Treatiſe of Fowling: <hi>Wherein is contayned diuers proper</hi> Deuiſes both of Baytes and others: with the making of Birdlime, the manner and order in vſing of it on your Lime-rods: with many other ſpeciall points, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining to that Exerciſe.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S to the ornament of the Ayre belongeth Birds and Fowles, (as <hi>Beda</hi> ſaith) which I meane in this Treatiſe to ſet forth. Birds be called <hi>Aues,</hi> as it were deuide without way: (as <hi>Plinie</hi> ſaith) for their waies in the ayre are not diſtinguiſhed in certaine, and birds with mouing of their wings diuide and depart the ayre: but anone after the flight the ayre cloſeth it ſelfe, leauing no ſigne or token of their paſſage and flight. And Fowles be called <hi>Volucres,</hi> and haue that name of <hi>Volary</hi> to flie: for Birds flie with wings, (as <hi>Iſidore</hi> ſaith) and therefore they be called <hi>Alites,</hi> as it were <hi>Alates:</hi> that is, mouing and rearing vp themſelues with wings: for they flie not without wings, nor areare themſelues from the earth vp into the ayre without the benefit of their wings or elſe a Bird is called <hi>Ales,</hi> and hath that name of <hi>Alendo,</hi> féeding: for he is fed of himſelfe that féedeth birds and fowles of heauen, &amp; giueth meat to all fleſh (as <hi>Iſidore</hi> ſaith.)</p>
                  <p>The condition and properties of Birds be knowne by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers things, by their ſubſtance and complexion: for the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of birds and fowles be made of two middle Elements that be betwéene the two Elements that be moſt heauy
<pb facs="tcp:11193:33"/> and moſt light: for in their compoſitions and making, Ayre and Water hath moſt maſtrie: and therefore they haue leſſe of earthly heauineſſe, and more of lightnes of the Ayre then Beaſts that goe on land and ſwim in water. By lightneſſe of the ſubſtance they be boren into the Ayre (as <hi>Iſidore</hi> ſaith) and the Ayre that is cloſed in the hollownes of pens and fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, maketh a Bird light, and diſpoſeth and maketh him able and helpeth him to mount vpward. Alſo the condition of Birds is knowne by generation, for they haue a feminal ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of kinde plight in them, &amp; by vertue therof they be kindly moued to increaſe their kinde by déede of generation, and to kéepe their kind in order: As it is ſaid of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> all Birds (ſaith he) and Fowles when they bring forth Birds lay Egs, though it cannot be ſéene in all for ſcarcity: and the beginning of a generation of a Bird, as it is ſaid, it commeth of the white, and his meate is the yolke: and after ten daies of the generation a Bird is full ſhapen in all parts, and the parts be openly diſtinguiſhed and knowne, but then his head is greater then all his bodie: and if the Egge-ſhell were then broken, the head ſhould be found bowed vpon the right thigh, and his wings ſpread vpon the head.</p>
                  <p>When the generation of all the members is perfectly made, and liniation and ſhape of the members, the ſhel brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth ſometime the eightéenth day, or the twentieth day, as it fareth in Hens, and then the Chickins come out of the ſhell aliue, being full ſhapt, and ſometime twaine out of one ſhell. Among all Beaſts that be in order of generation, Birds and Fowles be moſt honeſt of kinde: for by order of kind Males ſeeke Females with buſineſſe, and loue them when they be found, and fight and put themſelues in perill for them, &amp; be ioyned to them onely, as it were by couenant and wedding, loue and nouriſh, and féed only the Birds that they get, &amp; ſo kindly they déeme and know betwéene ſexe &amp; ſexe, male and female, except few (whoſe kind goeth out of kinde) as <hi>Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle</hi> ſheweth an example of the Partrich, that forgetteth his ſexe, that is, to vnderſtand the diſſolution of male and female,
<pb facs="tcp:11193:33"/> and ſo he ſaith, that the male leapeth vpon the male, &amp; the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male vpon the female. But of the Egges that come of ſuch treading come no Birds, but they be as winde-Egges, and take an euill ſauor of ſuch treading, and an euill ſtinch. And Birds and Fowles ingendering, kéepe couenable time, for in ſpring time when the generation commeth in, Birds cry &amp; ſing, males draw to company of females, and deſire each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of loue, and woe with beakes and voyce, &amp; build Neſts, and lay Egges, and bring forth Birds, and when the Birds be gendered, they féede and nouriſh them, and bring them vp, but when the office off generation is full ended, then they ceaſe off ſong, and depart from each other, &amp; come not toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther till the time of generation commeth againe.</p>
                  <p>Alſo Birds and Fowles be knowne by the places that they dwell in, for ſome Birds and Fowles, as me ſéemeth, loue company, and dwelleth nigh men, as Hens, Géeſe, Sparrowes, Storkes and Swallowes, and ſome dread and flye and be afraide of conuerſation with men, as Fowles of woods, of mountaines and marries, for by their diuers com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plections they ſéeke and challenge diuers manners of places to inhabite in.</p>
                  <p>As we may ſée in our owne country of England, ſome Fowles vſe ſome ſheires more then other ſome, and in ſome ſheires there come none of ſome Fowles at all: as they doe in other ſheires. For thoſe that be cold and moiſt of kind, vſe marſhes and Riuers for gathering of meate, and making of Neſts, for ſitting abroode, and for to bring vp and nouriſh their young. Birds and Fowles that bée of more hot and dry kinde, dwell on Mountaines and on high Rockes and ſtones, as Birds and Fowles that liue by pray: as Eagles and Fawlkons, and other ſuch, to the which, kinde giueth crooked Clawes and ſtrong féete.</p>
                  <p>Alſo ſome wood-Fowles vſe to dwell in Woods and thicke tops of trées, and ſome of thoſe be more milde then other, as Birds that ſing in ſommer time with ſwéete notes in Woods and Trées.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11193:34"/>
                  <p>And other birds there be that liue onely in fields, and vſe to be therein, and get their meate, and eate continually of the fruit of the earth, as Cranes and Géeſe both wilde and tame, and ſuch Fowles loue to dwell together, both on the ground and in the ayre, and goe and flie together in heards, and loue their owne kinde, and make a King among them.</p>
                  <p>Séeing I haue declared the nature and propertie of Fowles in the ayre, I thought good to ſet downe ſome rules belonging to Fowling, to help to further ſome in that practiſe, which would faine learne and hath no teacher: which both to the pleaſuring of them, and ſmall labour of my ſelfe, I haue done my good will.</p>
                  <p>Firſt of Fowling with Limetwigges, and how wée ſhould ſet our Limetwigges for ſortes of Fowle. You muſt chuſe Limetwigs of thoſe twigs that grow on the body of the Trée, and not of bow twigges, for that they be brittle and will not hold, but will ſnap a two, but the twigs that grow on the body of the Trée, are young bend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing twigs: and you muſt haue to your whole ſet, a thouſand luſt. There is alſo diuers other manners of Fowling, as with Nets, Springes, baites and ſnares, with diuers other. But to ſpeake firſt of Fowling with Limetwigs, as ſome are ſet low and ſome high, and that is as we know the haunt of the Fowle that vſes to that place, whether they be Géeſe, Duckes, Snipes, or Hearnes, or Craines, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther manner of Fowle that vſes to the place that you ſet your Limerods in. If you ſet your Roddes for wilde Géeſe, you muſt ſticke them in a manner vpright, and halfe a yarde a ſunder, which is almoſt narrow inough for a Snipe: if you ſhould ſtick them any cloſer, there would no Fowle venter in at all, for the wild Gooſe is the ſubtileſt Fowle of any: for when ſhe lighteth, ſhe lighteth moſt commonly in the déepeſt waters for feare of deceit, &amp; if ſhe come out of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to land, ſhe will ſpie to ſée if ſhe can ſpie any thing before her: if ſhe ſpy any thing, ſhe will into the water againe: but
<pb facs="tcp:11193:34"/> euer when you ſticke your Rods, ſticke them ſo that the tailes of your Rods may be towards the water, (if you ſticke them by any Riuer ſide) and the heads of your Rods ſtooping from the Riuer, that the Fowle may come with the Rods: for there is no Fowle that will come againſt the Rods, nor is able almoſt if they would: but being your Rods turned from the Riuer, they will be the bolder to goe onwards, and then they can no way eſcape. And ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſet your Rods about the whole plat that you ſet, with their tailes outwards, and their heads ſtooping inward, for the Fowle will be the bolder to goe amongſt your Rods, if they chaunce to light beſide them: but you muſt giue good attendance vpon your Rods, leaſt that the Fowle which is tangled doe picke themſelues and get away againe: but you muſt lye very cloſe leaſt that the Fowle doe chance to ſpye you: but if it bée ſomewhat darkiſh that you cannot eſpye whether there be any Fowle lighted among your Rods, then go to your Rods and giue aſhue, and if there be any they will flutter ſtraight and flye vpward: and if that there be none, then take your ſtaffe and beate the Riuers and Lakes within halfe a myle compaſſe once or twiſe, if you be able to compaſſe it, or more, and then ſhall you haue them reſort to your Limerods very thicke: for he that mindes to catch any, muſt ſo trauell that he leaue no Lakes or Springes vnſearched, and ſée that your Limerods bée ſet ſomewhat low, round about at the very entring, for that is good for all manner of Fowle: but if that they be ſet high within, it is good reaſon that the Fowle doth ſhut her wings before ſhe is altogether at the ground, and ſee that you doe ſet your Rods within one another, about thrée quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters or halfe a yard a ſunder almoſt: and if it fréeze hard, you muſt trim them with a little new Lime and Gooſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greaſe mingled together, and that will kéepe them long from fréezing. And if there be any ſpeciall place which Fowles doe reſort to, as in déepe waters and running Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, and that the Riuer is déepe that you cannot ſet your
<pb facs="tcp:11193:35"/> Rods in, then take a pole or a cord, and a long hay-rope that will winde round about the length of the pole, then take your Lime-rods, and ſticke them very thicke and looſe withall, and then lay your pole or poles ouer the Riuer, and thruſt the end of your pole within the banke, and tye the other end of your pole next to you to the banke ſide, and ſée that your pole be a prety way within the water, and that the heads of your Rods doe ſtand cloſe to the water: and thus may you ſet as many poles or cords as you thinke the place doth deſire, and ſticke your rods very looſely that they may goe with the fowle as ſoone as they touch them.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Good Spaniell a treaſure to Fowler ſure is,</l>
                     <l>To helpe him ſometime, elſe oft ſhould he mis:</l>
                     <l>For water and land, it is a good thing</l>
                     <l>A Spaniell to haue, his game for to bring.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>Alſo there is another manner of way to catch in the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, with ſmall cords being tyed ouerthwart the water, and lime them as you doe Lime-rods with good water-lime (as we call it) though indéed it is but Bird-lime, but it is tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to hold within the water, which it will doe if you let the cords be but a little within the water that it may ſcarce co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it: and if the water be broad, then take a Corke or two and tie them to your Line to hold it vp. This is a pretie way and not to be ſuſpected.</p>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>How to make Bird-lime very pure.</head>
                     <p>FIrſt pill the barke from the Holly-trée about Midſomer, then boyle the ſame barke, till the vtter rinde will pill from the gréene barke, which will be within one day, then lay the ſame inner barke ſo pilled in ſome cloſe place on the ground, and couer the ſame with ſome gréene wéeds or docks till it be well rotten, which will be within nine daies or there about, then eyther beate it in morters, or grinde it very ſmall, and then in ſome quicke ſtreame waſh it very cleane: then put it in a pot of earth, and it will ſpurge within
<pb facs="tcp:11193:35"/> thrée dayes, then take off the ſcumme twiſe or thriſe, for if there be any filth left in it, it would rot the Lime. After this keepe the Lime very cloſe till you haue néede to occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie it, mingle a little Hogs greaſe with it, and ſo may you worke your Rods with it. Therefore as it is mentioned of of the Poet, the Woſell or Robin is a great cheriſher of the Holly-trée, as <hi>Terence</hi> ſaith, <hi>Turdus cacat ſibi malum,</hi> he maketh a Rod for his owne tayle, for the doung of the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell cheriſheth much the Holly-trée, which afterwards turnes to his owne ſorrow.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>A rare ſecret to catch Fowle, as Geeſe, Duckes, or Birds.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>NVxe vomica,</hi> otherwaies called in Engliſh the Spring Nut, being a pretie deale of that ſod in a pecke of Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or as little as you thinke good, or Fetchis, or Wheat, and being ſtrowed where wilde Géeſe, or wilde Duckes come, and as ſoone as they eate of this, they will ſound, and you may take them with your hand. Alſo the powder of <hi>Nuxe vomica</hi> is good to kill Kites, Rauens, Pyes, Crowes, or any other carronous fowle. Alſo take a péece of fleſh and lay it in the field, and make holes in it, then put in the powder of <hi>Nuxe vomica</hi> in euery hole, and ſo ſoone as any fowle eates of this, they will be ouercome, and then they will flie, boult vpright, and fall downe to the ground ſtraight againe, and ſo you may take them.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Another pretie way to make Birds drunke that you may take them with your Hand.</head>
                     <p>TAke Wheat or Fetches, or any other ſéede, and lay the ſame in ſtéepe in lées of wine, or in the iuyce of Hem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke, and ſtraw the ſame in the place where Birds vſe to haunt, and if they eat thereof, ſtraightwaies they will be ſo giddie that you may take them with your hand.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb facs="tcp:11193:36"/>
                     <head>An excellent way to make a baite to catch wilde Geeſe, and wilde Duckes, and all other ſorts of Fowle.</head>
                     <p>TAke the ſéede of Belenge, and the rootes alſo, and ſtéepe them in water the ſpace of a day and a night: then ſéeth the ſaid ſéeds and roots in the water that they were ſtéeped in, ſo that the ſéeds may well drinke and ſoke vp the water, then lay the ſaid ſéeds or graine in the places where wilde Duckes and wilde Géeſe are wont to reſort, and they will eate this graine or ſéede ſo prepared, and thereupon will ſléepe as they were drunke, and in the meane time you may take them with your hands: but there muſt be a pretie quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie of this, eſpecially for wilde Géeſe. This may alſo ſerue to take all other manner of Fowle that goe together in ſholes or companies. If you ſéeth this graine in Brimſtone, and lay it in the places where Birds and Fowles are wont to féede, and all that eate of it will fall downe and die: but to kéepe them that they die not, you muſt giue them to drinke Oyle Oliue, and ſhortly after they will reuiue againe. This is approued.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of fowling with Lime-buſh.</head>
                     <p>TO ſpeake of Lime-buſh there can be but little ſaid, for it is commonly knowne and practiſed of all both in Winter and Sommer. In Winter it is vſed with Lime-buſh, which we call Bat-fowling, along by hedges to catch thoſe Birds that reſt in hedges, one to carrie a light and another to beat the hedge: as alſo the Lime-buſh is vſed at houſe ends, Houels or Ricks: the Lime-buſh is of little coſt, and is good for all times of the yéere. In Sommer you may call Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes with a whiſtle to your buſh. There is another pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie way to catch Birds with your Lime-buſh, if you can get but an Owle and ſet her vpon an hedge, and ſet a buſh or two of one ſide of her, and when the Birds eſpie her they will flutter about her, and you ſhall catch good ſtore of Birds. In Winter you haue many other waies good.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb facs="tcp:11193:36"/>
                     <head>How to fowle with Nets.</head>
                     <p>THere is another more certaine, and more plentifull manner of fowling, which is nothing at all paineful or vnwholeſome, the pleaſure &amp; neatneſſe being compared with the labour, and that is to fowle with Nets, of which there be diuers and ſundry kindes: of which I count the Day-net to be the moſt principall, both becauſe the vſe is neate, gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemanly, and mixt with a moderate exerciſe, ſuch as kéepeth the bodie warme without exceſſe of heate, &amp; quickneth both the eye and vnderſtanding with a ſharpeneſſe and vigilancy to obſerue the aduantages and motions which beguile the poore innocent Birds, theſe Nets likewiſe are moſt in vſe from the latter end of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> at what time the corne is car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away, till <hi>Chriſtmas,</hi> and the time of the day is from the firſt appearance of the Sunne till his declination: for you ſhall vnderſtand that the daies which are ſcouling, win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, rainie or miſtie are in no wiſe for this exerciſe. To ſpeake of the ſhape of theſe Nets, they muſt be two diſtinct and ſeuerall Nets of one length, breadth, and wideneſſe of maſh, the length would be about foure fadome, and the breadth a fadome &amp; ſomewhat better, the maſh would be inch and a halfe compaſſe, and the ſubſtance thereof the beſt and ſtrongeſt browne-thréed which can be made, looke how broad your Nets are ſo long at the full you muſt haue foure poales, which with a ſtrong round cord that runnes all the length of your Nets you muſt faſten at both ends of your Nets very ſtrongly and ſtifly, which being done, you ſhall ſée your Nets carry out their true proportion, in the full ſhape and manner as they were knit, riſing and falling as if they were of one ſubſtance, which done, you ſhall lay them on the ground if it be leuell &amp; ſmooth, ſo as they may ioyne edge to edge &amp; no more, and that when you will caſt them open they may riſe like a gate with two leaues or doores, and fall each <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>om other iuſt their owne quantities, lying vpon the ground flat, ſmooth, cloſe, and as it were vnperceiued, but if you
<pb facs="tcp:11193:37"/> ſhall lay them in the corne fields vpon lands, then you ſhall lay them ſo as they may eyther fall cloſe together in the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, or elſe vpon the top of the land ridge, and when they open or deuide that they may lie flat and cloſe eyther to the ridge or to the furrow, according to the aduantage of the ground. When you haue carefully ordred this, and laid your Nets in ſuch ſort as you would haue them lie when they are drawne inward, then you ſhall ſtake faſt downe to the earth with foure little ſtakes, the foure outmoſt corners of your two Nets, ſo that the Nets may riſe vpon thoſe ſtakes, to open and ſhut as vpon ſo many payre of hinges. This done, you ſhall lay the Nets open one from another, ſo that thoſe corners which was inmoſt may be outmoſt, and from the two farthermoſt corners which ſhall bee from you, haue two lines of ſtrong round cord of two fadom and a halfe in length a péece, and ioyning both the ends to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, ſtake them downe ſtraight &amp; faſt at their vttermoſt length as neare as you can geſſe with your eye in the midſt betwéene your two Nets, which done, you muſt haue two other cords of the ſame length at the other ends of the Net next vnto you, and ioyne thoſe ends likewiſe together with a knot or loope but by no meanes ſtake them downe, but let them remaine looſe, then to the knot or loope you ſhal faſten a ſingle cord of twenty yards in length, and your ſelfe going to the vttermoſt end therof ſit you downe vpon a little low haſſocke or ſtoole made of ſtraw or flags, not aboue a foot hie, (which you muſt haue prouided for the purpoſe, to kéepe you from the cold earth) and being ſo ſet, with all your ſtrength pull the ſingle cord vnto you, and you ſhall ſée the two Nets ariſe, and fall inward one to another ſo cloſe that they will ioyne and kiſſe together, thus when you ſée they doe yarely, nimbly, and at eaſe, you ſhall then ariſe and throw them open againe, &amp; then taking a liue Larke, or Bird, but the Larke is the beſt, which we cal the Stale, &amp; fixing her faſt to a long ſtick morteſſed in a ſtake, which you muſt faſten in the ground, yet ſo as the ſticke may moue vp &amp; downe, and at euery motion
<pb facs="tcp:11193:37"/> the Larke may flutter with her winges. This Stale you ſhall place in the middeſt betwéene your Nets, and hauing a long ſtring faſtned to the ſtale, which may reach to your owne ſeate: you ſhall lay it by you, and euer and anone with one of your hands pull it vp and downe to make the Larke flutter: which done, you ſhall haue a long Pole, hung about with ſhittle-cocks of feathers, which you ſhall place within thirtie or fortie paces of your Nets, ſo directly in the mouth of the Winde, that they may wherle and turne about with a ceaſleſſe motion: this will gather about you abundance of Larkes, and all ſorts of Birds: which being perceiued, you ſhall goe to your ſeate, and when you ſée any Larkes, or other Birds ſtoope or play about your Nets, or but come flying ouer your Nets, cloſe-by the ground, you ſhall pull your line, and all within the compaſſe of your Net is your owne, ſo you pull quickly and ſurely: then muſt you runne and take them out, and caſt your Nets open againe: and thus if the weather be ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, you ſhall haue ſport at your pleaſure: for I haue ſéene ſeauentéene, and eightéene dozen of Larkes taken in this manner in one morning. Theſe Nets are moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for the taking of Larkes, and other ſmall Birds, the Merlyn and the Hobby.</p>
                     <p>There is another Stale belonging to theſe Day-nets, which is very proper and excellent, chiefly at the latter end of the yéere, when Birds are leaſt apt to play: and that is a thrée-ſquare péece of wood, a foote in length, and three inches each ſquare: it muſt be painted red, and be all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laid with ſquare or round péeces of looking-glaſſe, it muſt haue a foote in the midſt, which muſt goe into a wide ſocket of wood, made in a ſtrong ſtake, which muſt be ſtricken into the earth, then to the foote muſt be faſtned a packthread, which being wounde many times about the foote, and iſſuing through a little hole of the Stake, muſt come to your ſeate, ſo that when you pull it, the wood will turne ſo round, that it will giue a ſtrange reflection, and
<pb facs="tcp:11193:38"/> ſo continuing the turning, it will intice the Birds to play wonderfully: the place where you ſhall ſet it, ſhall be by the ſtale your Larke, ſo that you may vſe one ſtring after another.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of taking Plouers with Nets.</head>
                     <p>IT is the nature of the Plouer, eſpecially the gray, which is euer the beſt, and moſt daintieſt, to flye together in ſhoales or companies, and for the moſt part they wil after féeding, haunt one place. The Nets wherewith you ſhall take them differ nothing at all from the Day-nets, eyther in ſhape or manner of laying, onely they muſt in quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie be full as bigge againe euery way as the Day-nets are: therefore when you haue found the morning or euening haunt of Plouers, you ſhall lay your Nets in the ſelfe ſame manner as I ſhewed you for the laying of the Day-nets, and as your Nets are larger, ſo your diſtance from your Nets, muſt be bigge and longer, and your ſelfe muſt lie cloſer, for if you can indure it, it is beſt to lie flat on your back, with your hands on your lines betwéene your legs: your ſtale muſt be a quicke Plouer. The houre for the laying of your Nets, is a little before day, in the morning, and a litle before the day be gone, in the euening: for the flight of Plouers, is at the ſpring of day, and at the cloſing vp of the day, when you may onely ſée and no more. I haue ſéene at one pull a dozen, and ſometimes two dozen taken, they come ſo cloſe and thicke together. As for the gréene Plouer, he is eaſie to be taken, either with Limetwigs, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ginnes, as hath béene formerly ſhewed vnto you.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>How to fowle with other Nets.</head>
                     <p>ALſo there is another manner of way to fowle which is with Nets, but the vſe of them is in the night, and the darkeſt night the better: and firſt of Fowling with Nets, which we call in England moſt commonly Bird bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and ſome call it lowbelling, and the vſe of it is to goe
<pb facs="tcp:11193:38"/> with a great light of Creſſets, or ragges of linnen dipt in Tallow that will make a good light, and you muſt haue a panne of plate, made like a Lanterne, to carrie your light in, which muſt haue a great ſocket to hold a great light, and carrie it before you on your breſt, with a Bell in your other hand of a great bigneſſe, made in manner like to a Cowbell, but of greater bignes, and you muſt ring it alwayes after one order, with two to goe with Nets one of each ſide of him that carries the Bell, and what with the light that ſo doth amaſe them, and the Bell that ſo doth aſtoniſh them, they will, when you come néere them, turne vp their white bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, which you ſhall quickely perceiue, then lay your Nets on them and take them: but the Bell muſt not ſtint going: for if it ceaſe, then the Birds will flye vp if there be any more nigh. This is a good way to catch Larkes, Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cockes, and Partriches, and all other land-Birds.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>To goe with a Trammill.</head>
                     <p>TO goe a trameling with a Net it is a good way, for two may goe a broad with a Trammill and catch ſtore. You muſt haue your Net ſeauen yards of length, and fiue in breadth: then take a couple of Poles or long rods, ſo long as your Net is, and tye your Poles to your Nets all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long the length of your Nets, one of one ſide, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the other ſide, then may you take your Pole in your hand, and plucke out your Pole out of bredth, and one goe in one thorow of the land and another in the other thorow, and goe along in lands, and carry your Net as farre for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards as you can, and when they heare you tread, then will they flutter vp into your Net, which you ſhall quickely heare, then let downe your Net to the ground, and gripe them, and take them from vnder your Net: but if it be in a very darke night, that you cannot ſée them, you ſhould haue a little cloſe Lanterne, that one may perceiue no light, but when it is opened to ſée to take them, but we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly make ſhift without.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb facs="tcp:11193:39"/>
                     <head>To ſet Springes.</head>
                     <p>ALſo ſome vſe to ſet Springes, which is made with a running knot, and a ſticke in the ground to yerke vp with another ſticke which the Fowle muſt tread on, which is in manner like to a trap or running knot which is made of haires, which is good to be ſet in froſt time, in ſprings, for Woodcockes and Snipes, or any other Fowle if they come where that ſpringes be ſet, or you may ſet them in Lands in the very thorow for Woodcocks, where you know that they haunt, and in Summer you may ſet them in buſhes eyther for Woodcocks or any other Birds, and you muſt looke that the ſticke that they tread on be ſomewhat round and browne, for if it be white, they will feare to tread on it: and your nouſe muſt be made of horſe haire, and the blacker the better.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>The end of Fowling.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:11193:39"/>
                  <p>A Briefe Treatiſe <hi>of Fiſhing: with the</hi> Art of Angling.</p>
                  <p>Wherein is contained <hi>the perfect making of all</hi> manner of Implements appertayning to that exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe: the diuers and ſeuerall Baytes for euery kinde of Fiſh, with the beſt times of the yeere for the taking of them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Iohn Helme,</hi> and are to be ſould at his ſhop in Saint <hi>Dunſtanes</hi> Church-yard in Fleetſtreet. 1614.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="4 (fishing)" type="book">
                  <pb facs="tcp:11193:40"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11193:40"/>
                  <head>A briefe Treatiſe of Fish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>with the Art of Angling: wherein</hi> is contayned the perfect making of all manner of Implements appertayning to that Exerciſe: The diuers and ſeuerall Baytes for euery kinde of fiſh, with the beſt times of the yeere for the taking of them.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the wiſe man ſaith, a good ſpirit maketh a merry and flouriſhing age, and cauſeth a man to liue long, and truly in my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, theſe thrée things are a medicine and a preſeruatiue for the ſame. The firſt of them is a merry thought. The ſecond is labour not outragious. The third is, diet meaſurable. The firſt, if a man will euermore be in a merry thought, and haue a glad ſpirit, he muſt eſchew all contrarious compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and all places of debate, where he may haue any occaſion of melancholy, and he muſt eſchew all places of Ryot, which is occaſion of ſurfet and ſickneſſe, and he muſt draw him to places of ſwéete ayre, and eate nouriſhing meats and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectable.</p>
                  <p>As now I meane to diſcribe theſe diſports and games, to finde the beſt of them as truly as I could, and although the right Noble and worthie Duke of yorke, late maſter of the game, hath deſcribed this Art of Fiſhing, and the reſt of theſe pleaſures and diſports. For hunting in mine opinion is labourſome, for the Huntſman muſt follow
<pb facs="tcp:11193:41"/> his hounds, ſweating full ſore, he bloweth till his lips bliſter, and when he thinkes he hath a Hare, full oft it is a Hedge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hog. Thus hée chaſeth vp and downe, and knoweth not ſometimes at what. He commeth home at night rayne-beaten and pricked, and his clothes torne all to péeces, wet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and all myrie, and ſome of his hounds loſt and ſome ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated. Such griefes and many other happen vnto the huntſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, which for diſpleaſing of them that loue it I dare not report: thus truly me thinketh it is not the beſt game, and diſport of the foure.</p>
                  <p>Hawking is labourous and troublous: for as often the Faulkoner loſeth his Hawkes, as the Hunter his Hounds, then is his game and diſport gone, yea, and full often he cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and whiſtleth, till he almoſt loſeth his wind, his Hawke ſometime taketh about, and giueth no minde nor ſight to him, for when he would haue her flie, then ſhe will bathe: with miſ-féeding ſhe wil haue the Frounce, and many other diſeaſes that bringeth to ſouce. Thus by proofe, this is not the beſt diſport and game of the ſaid foure. In my opinion the game of Fowling is the ſimpleſt: for in winter in cold weather, the Fowler can doe no good, but in the hardeſt and coldeſt weather, which is grieuous: for when he would go to his ginnes, he cannot for cold: many a deuiſe he maketh, and yet in the morning his fortune is hard, when he is wet vp to the waſt. Many diſcommodities I could ſhew, but for offending I let them paſſe. Then ſith it is ſo, that Haw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, Hunting, and Fowling be ſo laborous, that none of them may be a meane to a merry ſpirit, which is the cauſe of long life, vnto the ſayings of the wiſe in his Parables: doubtleſſe then it muſt follow, that Fiſhing with the Angle is moſt delectable, for all other are troubleſome &amp; laborous: For in ſome kinde of fiſhing it maketh the Fiſher, through wet, ſo cold, that many and ſundry times there enſueth diuers infirmities through the ſame: But the Angler he hath no cold, no diſeaſe, no impediment, except it be through himſelfe: for he can loſe but a Line or a Hooke at the moſt,
<pb facs="tcp:11193:41"/> which he may make againe at his owne leaſure, as he ſhall be taught hereafter: ſo then, is not his loſſe grieuous if the fiſh breake away with his Hooke, that is the moſt: for and he faile of one he hitteth of another: and if he quite faile, yet he hath his wholeſome walkes, his pleaſant ſhades, the ſwéete ayre, the excellent ſmels of the ſwéet Meddowe flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers, which maketh him hungrie: he heareth the melodious Harmonie of Birds and other Fowles, which he thinketh is better then the noyſe of Hounds, the blaſt of Hornes, or all the cry that Hunters, Faulkners, or Fowlers can make: and if the Angler doe take fiſh, then hath he a merry ſper it, and a glad heart. But who ſo will vſe this exerciſe he muſt riſe earely, which is profitable to man for the health of his body: For as the old Engliſh Prouerbe is, who ſo doth riſe earely ſhall be holy, healthie, and happie. Thus I haue ſhewed in this Treatiſe, that this diſport &amp; game of Angling, is the verie meane to induce a man to a merry ſpirit. And to the content of all thoſe that haue delight in theſe exerciſes, I haue collected this Treatiſe following, which you may vſe at your pleaſure. But yet before I procéede to this Art of Angling, I will ſpeake ſomething of the vſe of Nets, and how fiſh are to be caught therewith, for as Angling is for pleaſure and delight, ſo this is for profit and vſe for the Common-wealth, furniſhing Markets, and families, with ſuch prouiſions as are neceſſary for the foode and ſuſtenance of man. And of Nets you ſhall vnderſtand there be diuers kindes, as the great draught Net, the flewe Net, the ſhooue Net, the purſſe Net, and the leape Net, of all which I will giue you a little ſhort taſte or aſſay, yet ſuch as ſhall be large inough for your vnderſtanding and benefit: and firſt of the draught Net.</p>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The vſe of the draught Net.</head>
                     <p>THe draught Net of all other is the largeſt, for it is for Riuers, Ponds or large Waters: ſome are of thirty fadomes, ſome twentie, ſome fiftéene, and ſome tenne: it is
<pb facs="tcp:11193:42"/> made of the ſtrongeſt packthread, with a very ſmall and nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row maſh, in the midſt it draweth ſtrayter and ſtrayter downe, like a purſſe of a fadome and a halfe long, and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together excéeding cloſe in the laſt end, at which muſt be faſtned ſome heauy ſtone or other poyſſe, which may make it ſinke to the bottome: it muſt be in breadths a fadome and a halfe or better, which is the depth of any or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Pond or Riuer, the neather ſide muſt be all plummed with leade very thicke, to make it ſinke, and the vpper ſide muſt be full of floates, made of light Sallow ſuch as will not ſinke: at the two outmoſt ends, you muſt haue two ſtrong Poles, full as long as the Net is déepe, to whoſe ends you muſt ſtretch the ends of the Net, and then caſting it into the Pond, or Riuer, by ſtrong cords, which muſt be faſtned to each end of the Net, ſée you deuide the Net to each ſide of the Pond or Riuer, drawing it with great lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and conſtancie, being ſure that you neither pull the leads from the ground, nor ſuffer the floats to ſinke vnder the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, then you ſhall haue diuers men with long Poles or ſtaues, that ſhall goe on each ſide of the Riuer before the Net, &amp; beat vp the Fiſh, leauing none in any holes ſedges, buſhes, or ſuch like, but driuing them into the midſt of the water: then being come to the end of the Pond, or to the beſt landing place of the Riuer, thoſe with the poyſſe, bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the water that the fiſh may not paſſe by them, he on the contrarie ſide, ſhall bring ouer his lines, and bring the two Net Poles cloſe together, then caſting the floate a ſide from you, &amp; drawing the plummed ſide to you, you ſhall ſtoope downe and cloſe by the ground, leaſurely draw in the plumd ſide of the Net, another likewiſe with more leaſure draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the floats after you: then be aſſured, that what fiſh ſoeuer was within the compaſſe of your drawght, you ſhall finde it in the Rod of your Net, which as ſoone as you haue taken out, and clenced your Nets, well and ſufficiently, you may then if you pleaſe, caſt it in againe: and thus you m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> fiſh downe any Riuer as many miles as you pleaſe, or haue
<pb facs="tcp:11193:42"/> libertie ſo to doe, or elſe you may draw as many Ponds as are to your liking.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the flewe Net, and of his vſe.</head>
                     <p>THis flewe Net is a Net of ſome two fadome and a halfe in length, and one fadome in depth, made of a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſtraight maſh, and with a long rod in the midſt, the nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide plummed &amp; the vpper ſide floated: it is moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for ſmall brokes or little rundles, and the manner to fiſh with it, is in this ſort. You muſt firſt haue a ſtop Net, which is a plaine Net, without any rod, onely plummed, floa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and polde at both ends, and this putting into the brooke make it faſt to each ſide of the banke, then goe downe the Riuer from it ſome thréeſcore or foureſcore yards, and there caſt in your flewe, then make it likewiſe faſt to each ſide of the banke, ſo as you may be ſure that the plummets are at the bottome, and that there be a good place for the landing of your Net: then take your poyſſe, and goe to your ſtoppe Net, and there begin to beate, and ſo continue beating downe, till you come cloſe to your flew, then whilſt one bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth ſtill, let the other on the contrary ſide let looſe the ſlewe, and throwing the cords ouer vnto you, draw the ſlew lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurely in, and land it as you did your drawght-Net, and looke what fiſh was within that compaſſe of water, you ſhall finde it in the rod of your flewe Net, then taking vp your ſtoppe Net, put it in where you tooke vp your flew and ſo fiſh forward, and thus you may doe the whole length of a Brooke if you haue time and leaſure.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the Shooue-Net, or Purſſe-Net.</head>
                     <p>THe Shooue-Net and Purſſe-Net, are much what of one ſhape and making, being of a ſmall compaſſe, made round and faſtned to a great Bow of Wood ſet to a long Pole, they haue long rowes going from the Bowe, which like a purſſe, are gathered together in the neather end, the vſe of fiſhing with them, is moſt commonly in Pits, blinde
<pb facs="tcp:11193:43"/> dikes or other ſmall ſtanding waters, into which much fiſh is got by reaſon of inundations and ouerflowes of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. If therefore in any ſuch pits or little dikes you ſhall eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie any fiſh you ſhall take your ſhooue-Net and thruſting it downe to the bottome before the fiſh, you ſhall with your poy goe behinde him and beate the water, and as ſoone as you ſée him ſhut you ſhall ierke vp your Net, and be ſure to finde the fiſh in the rod thereof: if you draw your ſhoue-Net along any dike to that end which is ſtopt, or if there be no end ſtopt, then to ſome other perſon who ſtandeth a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie way from you beating the water with a poy, be ſure all the fiſh within that compaſſe wil be in the rod of your Net: This is a good Inſtrument for the poore-man, and oft get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth him foode when he wants it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the Leape-Net.</head>
                     <p>THe Leape net is a ſquare long Net ſet out with wood, hauing in it many rods or purſes which are diſtinguiſht from the outward Net with round hoopes of wood, it is moſt commonly faſtned to a leape, and laid in Mill dams, or in ſtraight waters, after any fall of great rayne which maketh a white water: it is moſt proper for the taking of Eeles, but becauſe it is to lye ſtill all the night or all the day, and thereby hath in it ſmall exerciſe or practiſe, I thinke it not méete to trouble your memory much therewith, but now to ret<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ne, and purſue my diſcourſe in land of the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Art of Angling.</p>
                     <p>IF you will be perfect in this Art of Angling, you muſt firſt learne to make your Implements: that is to ſay, your Rod, and your Lines of diuers colours: This done, you moſt know how you muſt angle, &amp; in what place of the water, how déepe, and at what time of the day, and for what manner of Fiſh, and what weather, how many impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments there be in fiſhing, and ſpecially in Angling, and what baite belongeth to euery Fiſh euery time of the yéere:
<pb facs="tcp:11193:43"/> And how you ſhall make your baytes bréede, where you ſhall finde them, and how you ſhall kéepe them for the moſt part: How you ſhall make your Hookes of Stéele, and of Oſmond, ſome for the Dub, ſome for the Flote, and for the ground. And here I will teach you how you ſhall make your Rod: you ſhall cut it betwéene Michaelmas and Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dlemas, of an ell and a halfe long, being the arme of a great Haſell, Willow or Aſpe, and beth him in a hot Ouen, and ſet it euen and ſtraight, and let it coole a month: then take a cord, and binde it faſt about, and binde it to a forme, or to a péece of ſquare timber: then take a Plummers wyer that is euen and ſtraight, and ſharpe the one end, and heate it in a fire of Charcole, and burne the hole quite through in the pith, beginning at both ends, and goe on to the middle: you may burne the hole with a Bird-broch, but let the laſt broch be bigger then any of them before, then let it lye and coole two dayes, vnbinde it and let it lye in the ſmoake, or the roofe of a houſe, till it be through drie. In the ſame ſeaſon cut a yard of gréene Haſell, and deth it euen and ſtraight, and let it drie with the ſtaffe: and when it is drie make it fit for the hole in the ſtaffe, vnto the halfe length of the ſtaffe: and to fill the other halfe of the crope, take a fayre ſhute of blacke Thorne, Crab trée, Medler, or elſe of Iuniper, cut in the ſame ſeaſon, and well bethed and ſtraight, and ſet them fit together, ſo that the crop may enter all into the ſaid hole, then ſhaue your ſtaffe and make it Taper-wiſe, then hoope the ſtaffe at both ends with long hoopes of yron, or latten, after the cleanlieſt manner, and a pike in the neather-end faſtened with a running wyer to take in and out of your ſtaffe, and ſet your crop a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full within your vpper end of your ſtaffe, in ſuch wiſe that it be as bigge there as in any other place aboue, then arme your ſtaffe downe to the fret with a Line of ſixe haires, and double the Line and fret it faſt on with a péece of a bowe: And thus you ſhall make you a ſtaffe to walke with, and no man ſhall thinke that you haue ſuch Implements about
<pb facs="tcp:11193:44"/> you: It will be very light and nimble to fiſh with at your pleaſure, and is alwaies very readie and neceſſary.</p>
                     <p>AFter you haue thus made your Rod, you muſt learne to colour your Lines of haire after this manner. You muſt take of a white horſe tayle the longeſt haires you can get, and the bigger and rounder they are the better it is, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part them into ſixe parts, &amp; colour euery part by himſelfe in diuers colours: as yealow, gréene, tawnie, browne, ruſſet, or duſkie colour: And for to make your haire take a good gréene colour, you muſt take a quart of Ale, and put into it halfe a pound of Allom, and put your haire and all together in a little Pan, and let them boyle ſoftly halfe an houre, then take out your haires, and let them drie, then take a pottle of faire water, and put it into a Pan, and two handfuls of Waxen, and preſſe it with a Tyle ſtone, and let it boyle ſoftly the ſpace of an houre: and when it is yealow on the ſcumme, put therein your haires, with halfe a pound of Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous beaten into powder, and let it boyle the ſpace of going of halfe a mile, and then ſet it downe and let it coole the ſpace of fiue or ſixe houres, then take out the haire and drie it, and it will be the beſt gréene for the water that can be, and the more that you put of Copperous to it the better it will be.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>For to make your haire yealow.</head>
                     <p>DReſſe it as before with Allom, and after with Oldes, or Waxen, without Copperous or Verdigreaſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>To make another yealow.</head>
                     <p>TAke a pottle of ſmall Ale, and ſtamp thereinto thrée handfuls of Walnut leaues, and put it together, and then put in your haire till it be as déepe as you will haue it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb facs="tcp:11193:44"/>
                     <head>For to make Ruſſet haire.</head>
                     <p>TAke a pinte of ſtrong Lée, and halfe a pound of Sote, and a little iuyce of Walnut leaues, and a quart of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom, put them altogether in a Pan, and boyle them well, and when it is cold put in your haire till it be as darke as you will haue it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>To make your haire browne.</head>
                     <p>TAke ſtrong Ale and Salt, and mingle them together, and put your haires two dayes and two nights, and they will be a perfect colour.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>For to make a tawnie colour.</head>
                     <p>TAke Lime and Water, and put them together, and then put your haires therein foure or fiue houres, then take them out, and put them into a Tanners Oſe one day, and it will be as fine a tawny colour as can be for your purpoſe.</p>
                     <p>The ſixt part of your haire, you ſhall kéepe ſtill white for lines, for the double hooke to fiſh for the Trout, and for ſmall lines to lie for the Roch and the Dace.</p>
                     <p>When your haire is thus collected, you muſt know for which waters, and which ſeaſons they ſhall ſerue, the gréene colour for all cleare waters from Aprill vntill September. The yealow colour in euery cleare water from September to Nouember. For it is like the Wéeds and other kinde of graſſe that is broken in the Riuer. The ruſſet colour ſerueth all the Winter vntill the end of Aprill, as well in Riuers as in Pooles or Lakes.</p>
                     <p>The browne colour ſerueth for the water that is blackiſh in Riuers or other Waters: the tawny colours, for thoſe Riuers or Waters that be heathy or mooriſh.</p>
                     <p>Now you muſt make your lines after this order, Firſt you muſt haue an inſtrument for the twiſting of your line. Take your haire and cut a handfull at the end, becauſe it is
<pb facs="tcp:11193:45"/> not ſtrong enough, then turne the top to the tayle ouer each alike, and make it into thrée parts, &amp; knit euery part by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and knit the other end altogether: then put that end faſt into your inſtrument into the clift, and make it faſt with a wedge, foure fingers ſhorter then your haire, then twine your warpe one way alike, and faſten them in thrée clifts alike ſtraight, then take that out at the other end, and let it twine that way that it deſireth, then ſtraine it a little, and knit it for vndoing, and that is good.</p>
                     <p>So when you haue ſo many links as will ſuffice for a line to make it long enough, then muſt you knit them together with a water knot, or a Dutch knot, and when your knot is knit, cut off the voyd ſhore ends a ſtraw breadth from the knot, thus ſhall your lines be fayre and euen: and alſo ſure for any manner of Fiſh.</p>
                     <p>The fineſt practiſe is in making your hookes, and for the making of them you may haue your ſeuerall kinde of tooles that you may doe them artificially. A ſéemy clam of yron, a bendor, a payre of long and ſmall tongues, and a knife ſomewhat hard and thicke, an Anuill, and a little Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</p>
                     <p>And for a ſmall Fiſh you ſhall take the ſmalleſt quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell Néedles that you can finde of Steele: and you ſhall put the Quarrell in a fire of Charcole till it be of the ſame colour that the fire is, then take it out and lay it to coole, and you ſhall finde it well alaide to file, then raiſe the beard with your knife, and make the point ſharpe, then alay him againe, or elſe he will breake in the bending, then bend him as he will ſerue for your purpoſe: you ſhall make them of great Néedles, as Shoomakers Néedles, Taylers Néedles, or Imbroderers Néedles: but looke that they will bow at the point, or elſe they be not good, and when you haue bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten flat the end of the hooke, fyle him ſmooth that it fret not the line, then put it into the fire, and giue it an eaſie red heat, then ſuddenly quench it in water, and it will be hard and ſtrong. And for to haue knowledge of your In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments
<pb facs="tcp:11193:45"/> that be neceſſary, without the which you are not able to accompliſh your deſire, that is, your Hammer, Knife, Pinſon, Claem, Wedge, File, Wreſt, and a Néedle.</p>
                     <p>When you haue made your hookes, then you muſt ſet them on according to their ſtrength and greatneſſe. Firſt take ſmall red ſilke, and if it be for a great hooke then double it and twiſt it, and for a ſmall hooke let it be ſingle, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with fret the line whereas you will haue the hooke ſtand, a ſtraw breadth, then ſet to your hooke and fret it with the ſame thrid the two parts of the length that it ſhall be fret in all, and when you come to the third part, then turne the end of your line vp againe double, to the other third part, then put your thrid in at the hole twiſe or thriſe, and let it goe each time about the yard of your hooke: then wet the hooke and draw, and looke that your line lye euermore within your hookes, and not without, and then cut of the lines end, and the thrid as nigh as you can, ſauing the fret.</p>
                     <p>Thus you know with how great hookes you ſhall angle to euery Fiſh, now I will tell with how many haires you ſhall angle for euery Fiſh. Firſt for the Menow, with a line of one haire: for the waring Roch, the Bleake, the Gudgeon, and the Ruffe, with a line of two haires: for the Dace and the Roch, with a line of thrée haires: for the Pearch, the Flounder, and Bremet, with a line of foure haires: for the Cheuin, the Breame, the Tench, and the Eele, with ſixe haires: for the Trout, and the Graſing, Barbell, and the great Cheuin, with nine haires: for the great Trout, with twelue haires: for the Salmon, with fiftéene haires, and for a Pike, with a chalke line made in the colour aforeſaid, armed with a line, as you ſhall heare hereafter. When I ſpeake of the Pyke, your lines muſt be plumed with leade, and the nereſt plumbe to the hooke, be a foote off at the leaſt, and euery plumbe of the quantitie of the bigneſſe of the line. There be thrée manner of plumbes: for a ground line, renning, &amp; for the flote: ſet vpon the ground line lying, ten plumbes, all ioyning together on the ground
<pb facs="tcp:11193:46"/> line, renning, nine or tenne ſmall: the floate plumbe ſhall be heauie, that the firſt plucke of any Fiſh may pull it into the water, and make your plumbes round and ſmooth, that they ſticke not on ſtones and wéedes.</p>
                     <p>THen you ſhall make your flotes in this manner. Take a péece of a Corke that is cleane without holes, and bore it through with a ſmall hot yron, and put thereinto a quill or pen euen and ſtraight: alwayes note that the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the hole, the bigger the pen, and ſhape it great in the middeſt, and ſmall at both ends, &amp; eſpecially ſharpe in the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther end, and make them ſmooth on a Grindſtone, and looke that the flote for one haire be no bigger then a Peaſe, for two haires as a Beane, for twelue haires as a Walnut, and ſo euery line muſt haue according to his portion. All manner of lines that be not for the ground, muſt haue flotes: and the renning ground line muſt haue a flote, and the lying ground line muſt haue a flote.</p>
                     <p>NOw I haue taught you to make your haires, hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter I meane to ſhew you the Art of Angling. You ſhall vnderſtand that there is thrée manner of anglings: the one is at the ground for the Troute, and other Fiſh: an other is at the ground at the Arch or ſtang where it ebbeth and flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, for Bleake, Roch, and Dace: the third is with a flote for all manner of Fiſh: the fourth, with a Menowe for the Trout without plumbe or flote: the fift is renning in the ſame for the Roch and Dace with two haires or one haire, and a flye: the ſixt is a dubbed hooke for the Troute or Grayling. And for the firſt and principall poynt in Ang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, looke that you kéepe you from the ſight of the Fiſh, either ſtand cloſe on the land, or behinde ſome Buſh: for if he ſée you, then your ſport is marde, for he will not bite, and looke that you ſhadowe the water as little as you can, for it is that which will make him be gon: for if the fiſh be fraide, he will not bite a good while after. For all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb facs="tcp:11193:46"/> of Fiſh that féede by the ground, you muſt Angle for them to the bottome, ſo that your hooke ſhall runne and lye on the ground: and for all other Fiſh that féedeth aboue, you ſhall Angle for them at the middeſt of the water, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the midſt, or below the middeſt whether ye will, for the greater the Fiſh, the nearer he lieth to the bottome of the water, and euermore the ſmaller the Fiſh, the more he ſwimmeeh aboue. The third good poynt, is when the Fiſh biteth, that you be not too haſtie to ſmite nor to take: for you muſt abide till the bayte be farre in the mouth of the Fiſh, and then tarry no longer, and this is for the ground: and for the flote when you ſée it pulled into the water, or elſe caried ſoftly vpon the water, then ſmite, and looke that you neuer ouer-ſmite the ſtrength of your line for breaking: and if it be your fortune to ſmite a great Fiſh with a ſmall line, then you muſt leade him in the water, and labour him there till he be drowned and ouerc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>e, then take him as well as you can, and euer take héede that you ſtraine him not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the ſtrength of your line, and as much as you can let him not goe paſt your lines end from you, but kéepe him euer vnder your Rod, and hold him as ſtraight as your line will ſuſtaine, and beare his leapes and his plunges as well as you can with your Crope and your hand.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Here I will declare vnto you, in what place of the water you ſhall angle, either in Poole or ſtanding water, and according to the deepenes of the ſaid water.</head>
                     <p>THere is no great diuerſitie in any place of a Poole, ſo it be déepe, for it is a priſon to all fiſhes, and therefore the ſooner taken: but in the Riuer the beſt Angling is where it is déepe, and cleare by the ground, as grauell or clay with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out mud or wéedes, and eſpecially if there be any whirling in the water, or a couert, as a hollow bancke or great rootes of Trées, or long wéeds fléeting aboue the waters, where the fiſh may hide themſelues at certaine times when they liſt. Alſo it is good to Angle in ſtiffe ſtreames, and alſo
<pb facs="tcp:11193:47"/> in vallies of waters, and in floud gates, and Mill pits, and at the banke where the ſtreame runneth, and is déepe and cleare by the ground, and in any place where the fiſh haunt and haue any féeding.</p>
                     <p>Now you ſhall vnderſtand the beſt time of the yéere, and the beſt times of the day, from the beginning of May to September. The beſt time of their biting is from foure a clocke in the morning vntill eight a clocke, and from foure in the afternoone till eight at night: but it is not ſo good in the afternoone as in the morning: and if it be a cold winde and a lowring day, it is much better then a cleare day: and the Poole fiſhes will bite beſt in the morning.</p>
                     <p>And if you ſee at any time of the day the Trout or the Grayling leape, angle for him with a Dub, according to the ſeaſon of the yéere, and where the water ebbeth and flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: the fiſh will bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e in ſome place at the ebbe, and in ſome place at the floud, after they haue had reſting behinde Stanges and arches of Bridges, and other ſuch places.</p>
                     <p>The principall time to angle in, is a lowring day, when the winde bloweth ſoftly: for in Summer when it is very hot then it is nought: from September vntill Aprill in a fayre ſunny day, it is very good angling, &amp; if the wind at that time haue any part of the Orient weather, then it is nought: and when it is a great winde and that it ſnoweth, rayneth, or hayleth, or is a great tempeſt, as Thunder or Lightning, or a ſwolty hot weather, then it is nought for to angle.</p>
                     <p>You ſhall further vnderſtand that there be twelue empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments, which cauſe a man to take no fiſh, as it doth moſt commonly hap. The firſt is if that your harneſſe be not fit and well made. The ſecond is if your baytes be not good and fine. The third is, if you angle not in biting time. The fourth is, if the fiſh be fraid with the ſight of man: The fift, if the water be red, thicke, and white, of any flood lately fallen: the ſixt, if the fiſh ſtirre not for cold: the ſeuenth, if the weather be hot: the eight, if it raine: the ninth, if it haile or ſnow: the tenth, if it be a tempeſt: the eleuenth,
<pb facs="tcp:11193:47"/> if it be a great winde: the twelfth is, if the winde be in the Eaſt, and that is worſt, for commonly neyther in Winter nor Summer, the fiſh will bite if it be in the Eaſt: the Weſt or the North is good, but the South is beſt of all.</p>
                     <p>And now I haue taught you to make your harneſſe, and how you ſhall fiſh therewith in all points. Now there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth to ſhew you what baytes be beſt for euery kinde of fiſh, for all times and ſeaſons of the yéere, which is the principall part of this Art: without the knowledge of which baytes, all the reſt before were to no purpoſe: for there is no man can make a fiſh to ſwallow the hooke without the bayte, and therefore I haue ſet you downe euery fiſh with his proper bayte belonging to the time, and beſt time to catch them as followeth.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>And becauſe the Salmon of all fiſh is the moſt Statelieſt, therefore I meane to begin with him the firſt.</head>
                     <p>THe Salmon is a very gentle fiſh, but he is troubleſome to take, for commonly he is in déepe places of great Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, and for the moſt part he will kéepe him in the midſt of it, that you may not come at him, and he is in ſeaſon from March vntill Michaelmas: in which ſeaſon you may angle for him, with theſe baytes, if you can get them. Firſt with a Red worme in the beginning and ending of the ſeaſon, and alſo with a Grub that bréedeth in a dunghill, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially there is a ſoueraine bayte that bréedeth in a water Dock, &amp; he biteth not at the ground, but at the flote: you may take him when he leapeth, in like manner as doth a Trout or a Graling, and theſe are approued bayts for the Salmon.</p>
                     <p>The Trout, becauſe he is a daintie fiſh, and alſo a very feruent biter, he is the next that I meane to ſhew you the time to catch him. From March vntill Michaelmas hée lieth on the grauell, and in a ſtreame you may angle for him with a line, lying or running, ſauing in leaping time, and then with a Dub, and earely with a running ground line, and in the day time with a flote line. You ſhall angle
<pb facs="tcp:11193:48"/> for him in March, with a Menow hanging on your hooke, by the neatherneſſe without Flote or Plumbe, drawing vp and downe the ſtreame till you féele him faſt. Alſo it is good to angle for him with ground lines, and with red worme, for the moſt part, and in Aprill take the ſame baytes, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the Canker that bréedeth in a great trée, and the red Snaile, you may take the Bob-worme vnder the Cowtord, and the ſilke worme, and the bayte that bréedeth on the Ferne leafe. In Iune take a red worme and nip off his head, and a Cod-worme, and put it on the hooke. In Iuly take the Cod worme, and the Red worme together. In Auguſt take a fleſh flye, and fat Bacon, and binde them together about the hooke. In September take the Red worme and the Menow. In October take the ſame. Theſe be ſpecially for the Trout at all times of the yéere. From Aprill vntill September the Trout leapeth: then angle for him with a dubbed hooke, according to the mouth: which dubbed hookes you ſhall finde in the end of this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, and the mouthes with them.</p>
                     <p>The Grayling, of ſome ſo called, of others Vmbre. It is a right delicate fiſh to mans mouth, and you may take him as you doe the Trout, and theſe are his baytes. In March and in Aprill the red worme, in May the gréene worme, a little braiſed worme, the docke canker, and the Hawthorne worme. In Iune the bayte that bréedeth betwéene the barke of an Oke. In Iuly a bayte that bréedeth on the Ferne leafe, and the great red worme, and nip off the head, and put it on the hooke, and a Codworme before. In Auguſt the red worme and a Docke worme, and all the yéere after a worme.</p>
                     <p>The Barbell is a ſwéete fiſh, but he is a very queaſie meate, and very dangerous to eate: for commonly he brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth an inconuenience to the Febres, and if he be eaten raw, he may be the cauſe of mans death, which hath often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times béene ſéene, and theſe are his baytes in March and in Aprill. Take freſh Chéeſe, and lay it on a Trencher, and
<pb facs="tcp:11193:48"/> cut it in ſmall péeces, the length of your hooke, then take a Candle and burne it on your hooke till it be yealow, and then binde it on your hooke with Fletchers ſilke, and make it rough like a Welbede, this bayte is good all the Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſeaſon. In May and in Iune take the Hawthorne worme, and the great red worme, and nip the head off, and put a Cod-worme on your hooke before, and this is a very good bayte. In Iuly take the red worme for the chiefe and the Hawthorne, together with the waterdock leafe worme. In Auguſt and for all the yéere, take the tallow of a ſhéepe, and of ſoft Chéeſe, each of them alike, and a little Honey, and temper them together till they be tough, and then put a little Flower into it, and make it in ſmall pellets, and that is a good bayte to Angle with at the ground, and looke that it ſinke in the water, or elſe it is not good for that purpoſe.</p>
                     <p>The Carpe is a daintie fiſh, but there is no great plenty of them, and therefore I write leaſt of him, but he is a very ſubtle fiſh to take, for he is ſo ſtrong in the mouth that there is no weake harneſſe will hold him: and as touching his baytes I haue little knowledge thereof, and therefore I would be loth to write more then I know and haue proued: but I am ſure the red worme, and the Menow are good baits for him at all times, as I haue heard diuers good Fiſhers report.</p>
                     <p>The Cheuin is a ſtately fiſh, and his head is a daintie morſell, there is no fiſh ſo ſtrongly enarmed on the bodie with ſcales, and becauſe he is a ſtrong biter he hath the more baytes, which are theſe: In March, the red worme at the ground: for commonly then he will bite there at all times of the yéere, if he be any thing hungry: In Aprill, the Canker that bréedeth in the trée, the worme that breedeth betwéene the barke of the trée of Oke, the red worme, and the young Froſhes when the féete be cut off: alſo the Stone Flie, the Bob vnder the Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turd, the red Snaile: In May, the bayte that bréedeth in the Ozier leafe, and the Docke canker put on the
<pb facs="tcp:11193:49"/> hooke, and a bayte that bréedeth on the Ferne leafe, the Red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worme, and the bayte that groweth vpon the Hawthorne, and a bayte that bréedeth on the Oke leafe, and a Silke worme, and a Codworme together: In Iune, take the Creker and the Dorre, alſo a Red worme the head being cut off, and a Codworm before, and put them on the hooke: alſo a Grub that bréedeth in the dunghill, a great Graſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and the Humble Bée in the Meadow: Alſo yong Bées and Hornets, and the Flie that is among the Piſmires hils. In Auguſt, take Wort wormes, and Maggots, till Michaelmas. In September, the Red worme, and a young Mouſe not haired, and the Houſe combe.</p>
                     <p>The Breame is a noble fiſh and a daintie, and you ſhall angle for him from March vntill Auguſt with a Redworme, and then with a Butterflye, and with a bayte that grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth amongſt gréene Réede, and a bayte that bréedeth in the barke of a dead trée: and for Bremets take Maggots, and from that time forward all the yéere take the Red worme: and in the Riuer, browne bread.</p>
                     <p>The Tench is a good fiſh, and healeth, in a manner, all other fiſh that be hurt, if they may come to him, he is moſt parts of the yéere in the mud, and ſtirreth moſt in Iune and Iuly, and in other ſeaſons but little: he is an euil biter, and his baytes be theſe: For all the yéere, browne Bread toſted with Honey, the likeneſſe of a bantred loafe, and the great red worme, and take the blacke bloud in the heart of a Shéepe, and Flower and Honey, and temper them all together, ſo make them ſofter then paſte and annoynt the Red worme therewith, both for this fiſh and for others, and they will bite much the better thereat at all times of the yéere.</p>
                     <p>The Perch is a daintie fiſh, and paſſing wholeſome, and a great and earneſt biter: In March, the Red worme, the Bob vnder the Cowtord. In Aprill and May, the Slow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorne worme, and the Cod worme. In Iune, the bayte that bréedeth in an old fallen Oke, and the great Canker.
<pb facs="tcp:11193:49"/> In Iuly the bait that bréedeth on the Ozier leafe, and the Bob that bréedeth on the dunghill, and the Hawthorne worme, and the Cod-woorme. In Auguſt, the red worme and Maggots, and all the yéere after take the red worme for the beſt.</p>
                     <p>The Roch is an eaſie fiſh to take, and if he be fat and pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned then is he good meate, and his baites are theſe. In March take the red worme. In Aprill, the Bob vnder the Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turd. In May, the baite that bréedeth in the Oken leafe, and the Bob on the dunghill. In Iune, the baite that brée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth on the Ozier, and the Cod-worme. In Iuly, the Houſe-flyes, and the baite that bréedeth on an Oke, and the Not-worme, and Mathews maggots, vntill Michaelmas, and after that the fat of Bacon.</p>
                     <p>The Dace is a gentle Fiſh, and is very good meat: in March his baite is a red worme, and in Aprill the Bob vnder the Cowturd. In May the docke canker, and the bayte on the Slowthorne, and that on the Oken leafe. In Iune the Cod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worme, and the baite on the Ozier, and the white Grub on the dunghill. In Iuly take houſe flies, and the flyes that bréede in Piſmire hils, the Cod-worme and Maggots till Michaelmas, and if the water be cleare, you ſhall take fiſh when other ſhall take none, and from that time forth doe as you would doe for the Roch: for commonly their byting and their baytes be a like.</p>
                     <p>The bleake is but a féeble fiſh, yet is he holſome. His baite from March til Michaelmas be the ſame that I haue written for the Roch and the Dace, ſauing all the ſummer you may angle for him with a houſe flye, and in Winter ſeaſon with Bacon, and with other baites, as hereafter you ſhall learne.</p>
                     <p>The Ruffe is a very good and holſome fiſh, and a frée biter: but ſubtile withall, and you muſt angle for him with the ſame baites &amp; the ſame ſeaſons of the yéere as I haue tolde you of the Pearch: for they be like in fiſh &amp; féeding, ſauing the Ruffe is leſſe, &amp; therefore you muſt haue the ſmaller baites.</p>
                     <p>The Flounder is a holſome fiſh and frée, but a ſubtile
<pb facs="tcp:11193:50"/> biter, in this manner: for commonly when he ſucketh his meat, he féedeth at the ground, and therefore you muſt angle for him with a ground line lying, and he hath but one man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of baite, and that is a red worme, and that is moſt chiefe for all manner of Fiſh.</p>
                     <p>The Gudgeon is a good fiſh of his bigneſſe, and he biteth well at the ground, and his baites for all the yéere is the red worme, Cod-worme and Maggots, and you muſt angle for him with a flote, and lot your baite be néere the bottome, or elſe vpon the ground.</p>
                     <p>The Menow when he ſhineth in the water is bitter, and though his bodie be but little, yet he is a rauenous biter and eger, and you ſhall angle for him with the ſame baites that you doe for the Gudgeon, ſauing they muſt be ſmall.</p>
                     <p>The Eele is a queaſie fiſh, and a rauenor and a deuourer of the brood of fiſh, &amp; the Pyke is alſo a deuourer of fiſh, I put them both behinde all other fiſh for to angle. For the Eele, you ſhall finde a hole in the ground of water, and it is blew and blackiſh, there put in your hooke till it be a foote within the hole, and your bayte ſhalbe a great angle with a Menow.</p>
                     <p>The Pyke is a good fiſh, but that he is a deuourer of all fiſh as well of his owne broode as of other, and therefore I loue him the worſe: and for to take him ye ſhall doe thus. Take a Roch or a freſh Herring, and a wyer with a hooke in the end, and put it in at the mouth, and downe by the ridge, to the tayle of the Herring, and then put the line of your hooke in after, and draw the hooke into the chéeke of the freſh Herring, then put a plumbe of lead on your line a yard from you hooke, &amp; a flote in the midway betwéene, and caſt it in a pit where the Pykes vſe, and this is the beſt and ſureſt way to take: and thrée manners of taking him there is. Take a Froſh, and put it on your hooke, betwéene the ſkin and the body, in at the necke, on the backe halfe, and put on the flote a yard thereto, and caſt it where the Pyke haunteth, and you ſhall haue him. Another way: Take the ſame bayt and put it in, ſafe tied, and caſt it into the water with a Corke, and you
<pb facs="tcp:11193:50"/> ſhall not faile of him: And if you minde to haue good ſport, then tie your cord to a Gooſe foot, and you ſhall ſée good haling bewéene the Gooſe and the Pyke, who ſhall haue the better.</p>
                     <p>Now you know with what bayts and in what ſeaſons of the yéere you ſhal angle for euery kinde of fiſh, now I meane to tell you how you ſhall kéepe and féede your quicke bayts. You ſhall kéepe them all in general, and euery one ſeuerall by himſelfe, with ſuch things as they are bred in, and as long as they be quicke and new they be fine: but when they be in a ſlough or dead, then they are nought: Out of theſe be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted thrée broodes: that is, Hornets, Humble Bées and Waſpes, which you ſhall bake in bread, and dip their heads in bloud, &amp; let them drie. Alſo except Maggots, which when they be bred great with their naturall féeding, you ſhall féed them furthermore with Shéepes tallow. And take héed that in going about your diſports you open no mans gates, but that you ſhut them againe. Alſo you ſhall not vſe this ſport craftily for couetouſneſſe, to the increaſing and ſparing of your money onely, but principally for your ſolace, and for the maintenance of your bodily health. For when you pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to goe on your diſports in fiſhing, you will not deſire greatly many perſons with you, which might let you of your game, and then your minde may be well giuen to the ſeruing of God, as in prayer or otherwiſe, and in ſo doing you ſhall eſchew and auoid many vices, as Idlenes, which is the principall leader to vice, and it is commonly ſéene that it bringeth diuers to their vtter deſtruction. Alſo you muſt not be too deſirous of your game, but with diſcretion, that you marre not other mens game, and your owne to, as too much at one time, which you may lightly do, if in euery point you fulfill this preſent Treatiſe: but when you haue a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient meſſe, to content your ſelfe for that time. Alſo you ſhall apply your ſelfe to the nouriſhing of the game, and in deſtroying of ſuch things as ſhall be the deuourers of it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
